<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Rebels doom, or, An historical account of the most remarkable rebellions from Edward the Confessor's reign to His present Majesties happy restauration : with the fatal consequences that have always attended such disloyal violations of allegiance.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58284</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">9601865</idno>
  <idno type="VID">43770</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264196969</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26975</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">09601865</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58284)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43770)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1339:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Rebels doom, or, An historical account of the most remarkable rebellions from Edward the Confessor's reign to His present Majesties happy restauration : with the fatal consequences that have always attended such disloyal violations of allegiance.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 100, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for Robert Clavel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Kings and rulers.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43770:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43770:1"/>
            <p>THE Rebels Doom: OR, AN <hi>Historical Account</hi> Of the Most Remarkable REBELLIONS FROM <hi>EDWARD</hi> the Confessor's REIGN, TO His Present <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> Happy RESTAURATION.</p>
            <p>With the <hi>Fatal Consequences</hi> that have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways attended such <hi>Disloyal Violations</hi> of <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Foelix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavel</hi> at the <hi>Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43770:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43770:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Opinion of the <hi>Hetrurian Princes,</hi> That the Power of <hi>Rome</hi> would remain Eternal, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less it should be Ruin'd by the Intestin Discords of its own Citizens; The same may be said of the <hi>English Monarchy,</hi> whose Diuturnity is Established upon the Rocks that Environ and Guard it. Did not Her Neighbours, dreading the fatal effects of <hi>British Unanimity,</hi> use th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir utmost endeavours to foment the Discontents of the <hi>Grreat Ones,</hi> and cherish the Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies of the <hi>Common People;</hi> which is the Reason that the Settled Government can never long rest in Qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, and that the People so often stagger in their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, if they do not altogether withdraw it from their <hi>Lawful Sovereign;</hi> For, shake the Foundations of <hi>Obedience,</hi> and immediately <hi>Rebellion, Sedition, Tumult,</hi> and <hi>Faction,</hi> rowle in with an <hi>Irresistable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation,</hi> and cover the fallen Ruins of all <hi>True Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom-preserving Subjection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Destructive Consequences of which, blinding un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking Men with their own <hi>Ambitious Politicks,</hi> bring those Unfortunate <hi>Mischiefs</hi> upon themselves, which perhaps their most <hi>Potent Enemies</hi> could never do. However, what can be expected from such as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon the <hi>Steerage</hi> of <hi>Reason,</hi> and suffer themselves to be Govern'd by the <hi>Giddy Perswasions</hi> of their
<pb facs="tcp:43770:3"/> own <hi>Disorderly Passions?</hi> For that there are several <hi>Occasions</hi> that inveagle Men to lay aside their <hi>Reason</hi> is plain; of which there is not the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st <hi>Argument,</hi> when <hi>Persons</hi> meditating <hi>Revolutions</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> will not give themselves the <hi>Liberty</hi> from the <hi>Ill Successes</hi> that have befallen Others, to Consi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er and be Admonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the <hi>Fatal Events</hi> that may pursue their own <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts</hi> of the same Nature.</p>
            <p>Therefore in this <hi>Wavering Age,</hi> that has b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en so apt to take all <hi>Opportunities</hi> to spurn against the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority</hi> of their <hi>Sovereign Prince,</hi> it may not be unseasonable to give the same <hi>Admonition</hi> to the <hi>Restless</hi> and <hi>Impatient</hi> of whatso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver is the <hi>Settl'd Government;</hi> which <hi>Isocrates</hi> the <hi>Orator,</hi> gave to his Friend <hi>Nichocles</hi> amongst the rest of his <hi>Pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tical Precepts,</hi> Not to keep any <hi>Societies</hi> or <hi>Clubs,</hi> but what are allow'd by the <hi>Government,</hi> and which was to avoid all <hi>Clandestine Consultations</hi> in reference to <hi>State Disturbance,</hi> which if they do not tend to the <hi>Overt Act of Rebellion</hi> or <hi>Sedition,</hi> are ridiculous; but if driven on to their common end, are still attended with a Thousand <hi>Cares, Anxieties, Fears, Terrors,</hi> and <hi>Tormenting Mistrusts,</hi> and generally at last most fatally Calamitous. For which he gives this <hi>Infallible Reason,</hi> That the more secure the <hi>Prince</hi> is, the safer also are the <hi>People;</hi> there being no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing that more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forces a <hi>Prince</hi> to <hi>Rigour</hi> and <hi>Severity,</hi> than the <hi>Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardness</hi> and <hi>Repugnancy</hi> of the <hi>Subject,</hi> to obey his <hi>Commands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Confirmation</hi> of these <hi>Truths,</hi> all <hi>Histories</hi> are so full of <hi>Examples,</hi> that there is no <hi>Age</hi> or <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> hardly the <hi>Reign</hi> of any <hi>Prince,</hi> which has not Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented
<pb facs="tcp:43770:3"/> the Miseries of the Unhappy <hi>Deviation</hi> from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ssary <hi>Instructions.</hi> The Mutinous and Head-strong <hi>Elections</hi> of <hi>Otho, Galba,</hi> and <hi>Vitellius,</hi> in ho short a time did they empty th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mselves into the <hi>Succession</hi> of the <hi>Flavian Family?</hi> Nor could the <hi>Roman Mutineers,</hi> when whole <hi>Legions</hi> bandyed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, tho' with their <hi>Arms</hi> in their Hands, Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous against the <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> resist the <hi>Frowns</hi> of th ir <hi>Lawful Commanders,</hi> according to that of <hi>Livy; No sooner the General ascended the</hi> Tribunal, <hi>but all their fierceness melted into nothing.</hi> The whole <hi>Army,</hi> but now all in an Uproar, could not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fend their <hi>Revolting Leaders, Triumphing</hi> so lately in their <hi>Loud Acclamations,</hi> from being publickly Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pp'd, and Beheaded, in the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dst of their <hi>Camp,</hi> so far from Murmuring, that they did not so much as sigh at the <hi>Severity</hi> of the <hi>Execution.</hi> For the <hi>Majesty</hi> of <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority</hi> scatters the <hi>Threatning Tempests</hi> of <hi>Tumult</hi> and <hi>Insurrection,</hi> as the <hi>Sun</hi> consumes the <hi>Gloomy Foggs</hi> of <hi>Winter,</hi> and serenes the <hi>Air</hi> of <hi>Clouded Government.</hi> Nor durst the <hi>Macedonian</hi> rage in the height of their <hi>Seditious Fury,</hi> withstand their <hi>Unarmed Prince,</hi> at what time he flew among the <hi>Armed Multitude,</hi> and dragged from their <hi>Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> with his own Hands to deserved <hi>Execution,</hi> the <hi>Capital Promoters</hi> of the <hi>Revolt;</hi> For though they fear'd not to Disobey, yet they were afraid to interpose between h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir <hi>Lawful Sovereign's Just Revenge,</hi> and the <hi>Merited Punishment</hi> of the <hi>Miserable Fomenters</hi> of their <hi>Disobedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at need we travers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Forreign Writers,</hi> seeing we have such <hi>Plenty</hi> of <hi>Presidents</hi> among our own <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43770:4"/> enough to convince the most <hi>Factious,</hi> if not <hi>Factious</hi> to <hi>Stupidity,</hi> how vain it is? And how fatal it has been to the <hi>Undertakers,</hi> to resist the <hi>Stream</hi> of <hi>Settled Government,</hi> and <hi>Machinate</hi> against <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Inheritance?</hi> Which ought to take the deeper <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression</hi> in the Minds of <hi>His Majesties Subjects,</hi> when they shall find how ill such <hi>Irregularities</hi> thrive in their <hi>Native Soyle,</hi> and what <hi>Blasted Harvests</hi> the <hi>Wounds</hi> of <hi>Rebellion</hi> produce in their own <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43770:4"/>
            <head>THE Rebels Doom: OR, AN Historical ACCOUNT Of the Most Remarkable REBELLIONS, &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>EDWARD</hi> the Confessor.</head>
               <p>WE shall Commence where the Truth of English History first begins to disperse the Clouds of Antiquity, in the Reign of <hi>Edward the Conf s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor,</hi> at what time we find <hi>Godwin</hi> Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> actually in Arms against his Prince, surrounded with vast numbers of the deluded People, whom he had incens'd agains<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Soveraign, under pretence that he had a greater kindness for For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigners, then his own Subjects.</p>
               <p>A disturbance that cost King <hi>EDWARD</hi> no small trouble upon a slight occasion. For <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stace</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:43770:5"/> Earl of <hi>Bulloign</hi> having married the Kings Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster by the Fathers side, happened to have come into <hi>England</hi> some time before, ouly to give the King a Visit, then lying at <hi>Gloc ster.</hi> Upon his return home, at <hi>Canterbury</hi> one of his <hi>Harbingers</hi> quarrelling with one of the Burgesses of the <hi>Town</hi> about Lodgings, chanced to be the occasion of his own Death; which when his Lord heard of, in revenge, he slew eighteen of the Citizens in the heat of his fury. On the other side, the Citizens in as great a rage betook themselves to their <hi>Arms,</hi> and slew twenty of his Retinue, wounding many more, and putting the Earl to retire. Upon whose Complaint to the King of the Injury done him; <hi>E. Goodwin</hi> was commanded by the King to see Execution done upon the offenders. Here <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wins</hi>'s Ambition took its Opportunity to ingratiate himself with the People, to which purpose he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised the King to Examine the Cause, before he put his true Subjects to Death, at the Instigation of Strangers: Whereat, though King <hi>Edward</hi> were highly offended, yet it gained the Politick Earl what he sought for, the Affection of the Commons. Moreover the Arch-Bishop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> a <hi>Norman,</hi> and <hi>Goodwin</hi>'s Capital Enemy, made the Breach wider; incensing the King, that <hi>Godwins</hi> Refusal of his Command, was an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Contempt,</hi> wherein more Dangers lay concealed then were to be endured. Upon which the King called an <hi>Assembly</hi> of <hi>Estates,</hi> and appointed a day of Meeting at <hi>Glocester.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43770:5"/>
               <p>The Commons (whose common Custom it is mortally to hate all Strangers, though for reasons of which, they can give no account) seeing, or at least being made beleive that <hi>E. Godwin</hi> was in danger for his care of their Priviledges, were ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily drawn to revolt from their Soveraign, to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist the Earl and his Popular Cause, and in a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Posture guarded his person at <hi>Beverstame</hi> not far from the King.</p>
               <p>The Estates being met, <hi>Godwin</hi> who was sent for, refused to attend, pretending Service against the <hi>Welsh,</hi> so that now suspitions on both sides encreasing, great preparations were made on both sides. To the King repaired several of the most powerful Nobility: To <hi>E. Godwin</hi> the People of <hi>Southwark</hi> and <hi>Kent:</hi> His Son <hi>Swain</hi> brought him the Men of <hi>Oxford, Somerset, Hereford, Gloc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ster</hi> and <hi>Berkshire,</hi> to which his Son <hi>Harold</hi> joyned those of <hi>Essex, Norfolk, Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Huntington<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire.</hi> So that being now surrounded with a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Army, he made no scruple to send a Bold and Trayterous Message to the King, to have the Earl of <hi>Bulloign,</hi> with all his <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> then in the Castle of <hi>Dover,</hi> delivered to him and his Sons. Which being by the King refused (as it was but reason) the haughty Earl prepared to give his <hi>Soveraign</hi> Battle: But the more prudent, guided by their foresight of the Imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, threatning the Kings Person, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Consequences on both sides, probably to be expected, laboured so industriously, that the whole matter was at last referred to a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43770:6"/> to be held at <hi>London,</hi> with all convenient speed.</p>
               <p>In order to this Agreement, King <hi>Edward</hi> strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guarded with an Army of <hi>Mercians</hi> and <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumbrians,</hi> enters <hi>London,</hi> while <hi>Godwin</hi> and his <hi>Son,</hi> with an attendance no less formidable, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters himself at his own House in <hi>Southwark.</hi> But then his Army wavering, and as bad causes and consciences make men do, suspecting the worst, by little and little shrunk away from him, which being known to the King, he presently pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Sentence</hi> of Banishment against the Rebel <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi> and his five <hi>Sons,</hi> without farther proceeding by way of Parliament, as he had determined. Thereupon <hi>Godwin</hi> with a vast Mass of Wealth, and three of his <hi>Sons</hi> failed into <hi>Fland rs,</hi> while the other two passed into <hi>Ireland;</hi> who being thus dispersed, were by the King proclaimed Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laws.</p>
               <p>In the second year of his Banishment, <hi>Godwin</hi> and his three <hi>Sons,</hi> having furnished himself with several <hi>Ships</hi> of War, came upon the Coasts of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Sussex,</hi> where they landed and returned laden with <hi>Spoiles.</hi> The like did <hi>Harold</hi> and <hi>Leof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win,</hi> his two other <hi>Sons,</hi> upon the Coasts of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merset</hi> and <hi>Devonshire,</hi> whence coasting about the point of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> they joyn'd their Fathers Fleet near the Isle of <hi>Wight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King not enduring the Insolence of these Outlaw'd Rebels, with a Navy of sixty <hi>Ships</hi> well fitted for War, intended to have made an end of those Rebellious Devestations, by the Destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43770:6"/> of the Disloyal <hi>Godwin</hi> and his <hi>Sons:</hi> But the Fleets being ready to engage, such a thick Fog overspread the <hi>Sea,</hi> that the Fleets could not see one another; at what time <hi>Godwin</hi> and his Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices were driven by contrary Winds, to the place from whence they came. However King <hi>Edward</hi> still jealous of his Return, set forth a Navy of forty stout <hi>Ships</hi> to secure the <hi>Seas,</hi> who did not keep so strict a watch, but that <hi>Godwin</hi> slipped by them, and having gained the People of <hi>Kent, Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex</hi> and <hi>Surrey</hi> to his Assistance, entered the <hi>Thames,</hi> where he did the like to those of <hi>London,</hi> who accepted of his Arrival, though King <hi>Edward</hi> lay there, so that without disturbance, his Navy warp'd up with a Tide through the South-Arch of the Bridg, while a mighty Army mustered to his aid upon the same side of the River.</p>
               <p>Thus the Nobility finding English against En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, ready to embrue their hands in each others Blood, wrought so far with the King and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Subject, that conditions of Peace were agreed on, and pledges delivered for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Godwin</hi> now restored to the Kings favour, might seem to have prospered by his Rebellion, and to have gained by the Breach of his Allegiance, to his Lawful Soveraign; but if he were too power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the King to punish for his misdeeds, yet he could not escape the Vengeance and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of <hi>Heaven,</hi> which prosecuted him so far, that he was suddainly surprized with the stroke of Death, as he sat at Table with that Soveraign
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43770:7"/> Prince of his, to whom he had given so much vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and rebellious Trouble, contrary to his sworn Fealtie and Homage.</p>
               <p>Nor were his Counsels less Traiterous than his Actions: For by his continual incensing the King against his vertuous Wife, he abstained obstinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from her Bed, by which means he left the Kingdom Heirless, and at last subjected it to a Forraign Race.</p>
               <p>Therefore was he punish'd by the hand of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> as we have heard, in his own person; and afterwards in the Persons of two Sons, <hi>Swain</hi> and <hi>Harold.</hi> The first of which was murdered by the <hi>Saracens:</hi> His other Son <hi>Harold,</hi> who had taken part with his Father in his Rebellious Practises, as one whom <hi>Heaven</hi> had decreed to depress, accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither the good Councel of his <hi>Fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nds,</hi> nor the offers of the <hi>Norman,</hi> was forced to surrender his life and usurped Kingdom, to the punishment of his Treasons to his Prince, and his perjury to the Conquerour, as if he had been only set up by the hand of Providence for a while, to bury the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <hi>English</hi> in his Ruins, and render him the more Illustrious mark of Divine Vengeance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>WILLIAM</hi> I.</head>
               <p>What ever opinion the <hi>English</hi> might have of the <hi>Norman,</hi> being as yet no more then a Duke, and looked upon as their Invad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r and Conquerour, while <hi>Edgars</hi> Title had several Abettors of great Birth and Power, I will not dispute. But when
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43770:7"/> the Kingdom had once acknowledged King <hi>William</hi> their Soveraign, and set the Crown upon his <hi>Head,</hi> when the Prince had taken his Coronation Oath, and they as his <hi>Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cts</hi> had sworn to him Fealty and Homage, then for the <hi>Northumbrians</hi> to take Arms, though it were for the recovery of their former Liberties, and for the Citizens of <hi>Exet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> to shut their Gates against <hi>Him,</hi> was absolute Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. The Citizens of <hi>Exeter</hi> were not only content to shut their Gates against their <hi>Soveraign,</hi> but contemptuously to flout and revile Him, till the very stones ashamed of so much Insolence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a King, fell down of themselves, and sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendered the Rebels that trusted in their defence, to the Mercy of their incensed Prince.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Northumbrians,</hi> they were so fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, as to overthrow the Kings Lieutenant whom he sent against them, but when the King himself drew near them in Person, the very terrour of his <hi>Approach</hi> daunted all their farther <hi>Attempts,</hi> so that he easily took several of the Chief Authors of the Rebellion, of which he punished some by cutting off their <hi>Hands,</hi> and others by taking off their <hi>Heads,</hi> according to the merits of their Crime.</p>
               <p>Nor did it fare better with <hi>Ralph de Ware,</hi> Earl of <hi>Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Norfolk,</hi> who upon his Wedding day, perswaded his Guests into open Rebellion, having also inveagled his Brides Brother into the same Conspiracy. But though King <hi>William</hi> were then in <hi>Normandy,</hi> so fair an opportunity availed them nothing; forsaken in their extremity by those they most trusted, and betrayed by one of their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43770:8"/> own party, the Earl of <hi>Northamp.</hi> the one was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to perpetual Imprisonment, and the other constrain'd to fly his Country and live in Exile.</p>
               <p>Nor may we here omit the unnatural <hi>Rebellion</hi> of his own <hi>Son,</hi> whose impatient Ambition claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Fathers Inheritance before the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture gave it <hi>Him,</hi> or that his Father was willing to resign it to him, fermented his hasty fury to that height, that he brake forth into open <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> against his <hi>Soveraign</hi> that begot him, insomuch that the business came to a battle, wherein the <hi>Son</hi> wounded the Father, and bore him off his <hi>Horse</hi> to the Ground. But what was the issue of this Disobedience? For the Dishonour done to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Disloyalty for his unnatural Arms, he lived afterward bitterly cursed by his own Parent; who execrated the time when he begat <hi>Him.</hi> Which Curses pursu'd him so violently, that what he so rapaciously and unseasonably endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to wrest out of his Fathers <hi>Hands,</hi> he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when he was in <hi>Possession</hi> of it, lost to his Brother <hi>Henry,</hi> was by him bereft of both his Eyes, and after <hi>twenty Years Imprisonment</hi> in the Castle <hi>Caodiffe,</hi> there miserably ended his days.</p>
               <p>The words of <hi>King William</hi> himself are very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable to our purpose. In <hi>Normandy,</hi> saith he, <hi>my Forraign Foes have risen up against me; yea my inward Friends I may say have invaded me: My Son</hi> Robert <hi>and other Younglings whom I have brought up and given Armes, have rebelled; to whom my false Clients and Subjects have given their Assistance, but they have not prospered, God, whose Servant I am,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43770:8"/> ever defending me, neither have they got any thing of mine, besides Iron in their Wounds.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>WILLIAM</hi> II.</head>
               <p>In this Kings Reign, <hi>Odo</hi> Bishop of <hi>Bayeux,</hi> the Kings Uncle, out of a spleen taken against <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frank</hi> the Arch-bishop complotted the <hi>Downfal</hi> both of the one and the other, to which purpose, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Conspiracy, <hi>Roger</hi> Earl of <hi>Hereford,</hi> with several other of the Nobility, he wrote Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into <hi>Normandy</hi> to his Nephew Duke <hi>Robert,</hi> hastning him to recover his right against his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then King of <hi>England</hi> by his Fathers Will; which he promised should be soon effected by his means.</p>
               <p>Duke <hi>Robert</hi> being easily drawn into this Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, the Bishop was the first that appeared in the Action, and fortifying <hi>Rochester</hi> began to set all <hi>Kent</hi> in a Combustion. His accomplices encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd by his example, did the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke in other parts of the Kingdom; for in the <hi>West, Robert Mowbray</hi> Earl of <hi>Northumberland</hi> assisted by another Bishop sack'd <hi>Bath,</hi> and fortifyed the Castle of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>istow</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the King. In <hi>Norfolk Roger Bygod,</hi> in <hi>Lë<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Hugh Grentemeisnel</hi> wasted those Counties. <hi>Roger Montgomery</hi> assisted by the Bishop of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> the Kings Domestick Chaplain, harrassed the County of <hi>Worcester</hi> with Fire and Sword.</p>
               <p>The Kingdom thus in a Rebellious uproar, and <hi>Rufus</hi> thus turmoiled, raises an Army of his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Subjects, which he first led into <hi>Kent,</hi> took
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43770:9"/> the Castles of <hi>Tunbridge</hi> and <hi>Horn,</hi> besieged <hi>Odo</hi> in the Castle of <hi>Pomsey,</hi> which he constrained him to surrender, together with the Castle of <hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> and then having deprived him of all his Lands and Livings in <hi>England,</hi> banish'd him out of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Duke <hi>Rob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt</hi> having by this time set footing in <hi>England,</hi> when he saw the main Pillar of his hopes thus fallen, made peace with his Brother, return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back into <hi>Normandy,</hi> and left the rest of the Conspirators at the Kings mercy, to make what Compositions they could for themselves. And thus the vain Project of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aspiring <hi>Prelate</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his King and Soveraign, vanished into smoke.</p>
               <p>Not long after <hi>Robert Mowbray</hi> before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Anco,</hi> with others, conspired to deprive the <hi>King</hi> both of his <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> and to have set up <hi>Stephen de Albemarle</hi> his <hi>Aunts Son.</hi> The fatal event of which <hi>Treason</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by surprizing <hi>Roger de Mowbray,</hi> who for his former Treachery and this, dyed a Prisoner. <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Ancho</hi> was punished with the loss of both his <hi>Eyes</hi> and his <hi>Virelities:</hi> And <hi>William Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merick</hi> another of the <hi>Conspirators,</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, Kinsman and Sewer cruelly whipp'd, and afterwards all naked as he was and besmeared with his own Goare, more Ignominiously hang'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:43770:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>HENRY</hi> I.</head>
               <p>In the Reign of this <hi>King,</hi> several <hi>Male-cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nts</hi> of whom the Chief was <hi>Robert Beliasme</hi> Earl of <hi>Shrews<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> affecting alteration, beheld with a <hi>Malignant Eye,</hi> the Glory of His beautious <hi>Crown: Robert</hi> as the most powerful, fortified the <hi>Towns</hi> of <hi>Shrewsbury, Bridgnorth, Arundel</hi> &amp; <hi>Tick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hil,</hi> with <hi>Victuals, Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> and allur'd the fickle <hi>Welshmen</hi> to his designs, of which the <hi>King</hi> having <hi>Intelligence</hi> march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into those parts with a <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erful Army,</hi> recovered <hi>Bridgn'</hi> compelled <hi>Shrewsb'</hi> to send him the Keys of her <hi>Gates,</hi> and at length constrained <hi>Beliasme</hi> &amp; other Heads of the Rebels to abjure the Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m for ever.</p>
               <p>In his Territories beyond Sea, the Earl of <hi>Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi> conspiring with <hi>Hugh</hi> Earl of <hi>Mantfort</hi> against their Soveraign, and breaking forth into actual <hi>Reb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llion,</hi> were by the <hi>Kings</hi> Lieutenant in those parts trained into an <hi>Ambush</hi> laid for that purpose, and being both taken alive, were delivered up by the Victor to the revenge of their offended Prince.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>HENRY</hi> II.</head>
               <p>Against <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. <hi>Hugh de Mortimer</hi> stufft his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles of <hi>Glocester, Wigmore</hi> and <hi>Bridgnorth,</hi> with <hi>Rebellious Garrisons,</hi> for no other reason, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he would not be under his Soveraigns Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul, but he was soon tamed by the <hi>King,</hi> who suddenly reduced all his Castles to <hi>Obedience</hi> with very little labour or expence.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Troubles</hi> which he had from his <hi>Son,</hi> after he had caused him to be <hi>Crowned King</hi> with himself, and given him a share of his <hi>Royal Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43770:10"/> Authority,</hi> they might be called an unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and ingrateful <hi>Retaliation</hi> of <hi>Paternal Kindness,</hi> yet it could not be said to be a <hi>Rebellion</hi> of one Crowned <hi>Head</hi> against another. Nevertheless they who advanced the unjust <hi>Pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntions</hi> and <hi>Animosi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of the <hi>Son</hi> were no way to be excused: They who blew the Coles of Dissention, and were the chief <hi>Incendiaries</hi> of the <hi>Divisions</hi> between the <hi>Crown'd Son,</hi> and <hi>Diademn'd Father;</hi> I mean those that were no less the Subjects of the one then the other were equal Traitors to both. Therefore did <hi>Providence,</hi> meaning only to Chastize the <hi>King,</hi> and not to deliver him up into his <hi>Enemies Hands,</hi> destroy those hopes that mov'd the <hi>Son</hi> to his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Attempts: So that the Earl of <hi>Leicester,</hi> one of the most violent <hi>Fire brands</hi> in that <hi>Disunion,</hi> one who was not contented to have affronted <hi>King Henry</hi> the Father, in the behalf of his young Lord and Master, but is Recorded to have laid his daring <hi>Hand</hi> upon <hi>His Sword</hi> to have struck the <hi>King,</hi> had he not been withheld, was encountred by several of the Loyal Nobility stedfast to the <hi>Old King,</hi> and with the <hi>loss</hi> of <hi>five Thousand</hi> of <hi>his Flemings, Himself</hi> and <hi>His Amazonian Countess</hi> taken <hi>Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> and carryed over ito <hi>Normandy,</hi> where at that time the <hi>Old King</hi> was, to be at his disposal.</p>
               <p>And it is observable, that <hi>His Son Richard</hi> the <hi>First,</hi> though he had a deep <hi>Hand</hi> in these <hi>Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> against his Father, yet when he came to the <hi>Crown,</hi> he banished from his Familiarity, and hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all those who had forsaken his Father, and both retained and enriched those other, who had Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43770:10"/> stood for the Elder King at all times, both against his Brother and Himself.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>King <hi>JOHN.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Reign of this magnanimous Prince was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a continual contest against Treason and Disloyalty, as well <hi>Ecclesiastick</hi> as <hi>Secular.</hi> Which were the two <hi>Handles</hi> that <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France</hi> took hold off, to wrest the <hi>Dukedom</hi> of <hi>Normandy</hi> from his <hi>Dominion.</hi> Never did Prince with more <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution,</hi> or with more <hi>Success,</hi> oppose the <hi>Power</hi> of his Forreign Enemies, till the Infidelity of his own haughty Prelates gaves his Barons the <hi>Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity</hi> to manacle his victorious Arms. For by the <hi>Traiterous Contention</hi> of a <hi>Proud Monk,</hi> advanced to the Primacy of <hi>England</hi> by the humble Order of <hi>Cloistered Monks</hi> at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> without the Kings knowledge or consent, and upon the <hi>Election</hi> of a another by the <hi>Kings Approbation,</hi> disclaiming his subjection to his <hi>Lawful Prince</hi> and appealing to the <hi>Pope,</hi> an equal match for <hi>English Princes</hi> at that time, the <hi>Kings Affairs</hi> were strangely disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. The <hi>Barons</hi> also from <hi>Arch-Bishop Huberts</hi> treasonable Doctrine preached before 'em, when they were preparing for the <hi>King's Inauguration, That the Crown of</hi> England <hi>was meerly</hi> Arbitrary, <hi>and at the</hi> Peoples <hi>Devotion;</hi> and from their own unwillingness to foregoe that uncontroulable great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, to which they had habituated themselves through <hi>King Richard's</hi> long absence in the <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y-Land,</hi> had suckt the <hi>Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ples</hi> of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> nor would be brought to swear other then conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43770:11"/>
                  <hi>Fealty</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> that is, they would no longer keep <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> to their Soveraign, then he continue to them their <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties.</hi> For under those specious <hi>Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> they covered their <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious</hi> designs to copemate their Prince, and put undue Restraints upon Regality. This <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce</hi> well underst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, and therefore sedulously kept up the <hi>humour</hi> amongst the <hi>Rebellious Barons,</hi> and sed the craving Appetite of <hi>Disloyal Hub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt</hi> with Golden Morsels, who thereupon was no less dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to cross the <hi>Kings Designs,</hi> by a dexterous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the perverseness of the Nobility, whenever he attempted to repair his <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Losses.</hi> Which <hi>Combinati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> was carried on with more secres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e while <hi>Hubert</hi> lived, for then he could make use of his <hi>Legative P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wer</hi> to countermand the <hi>Kings Commands</hi> as he pleased, and the Barons could pretend Reverence to the <hi>Holy See</hi> for their Disobedience, which <hi>Treachery</hi> of his, when the <hi>King had discovered,</hi> he dyed for grief, and the <hi>King</hi> after his <hi>Death</hi> had the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> to seize his ill got <hi>Wealth</hi> and vast <hi>Poss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssions,</hi> too unweildy for a Church man, in part of amends for the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of his Life.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Hubert</hi> being dead, the Proceedings of the <hi>Barons</hi> were then more open, but still the <hi>Church</hi> contentions gave them their chiefest Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunies. For upon <hi>Reginald</hi> the <hi>Monk's</hi> Appeal to <hi>Pope Innocent,</hi> the cunning <hi>Roman</hi> set aside both <hi>Reginalds</hi> claim, and the Bishop of <hi>Norwich's</hi> chosen by the <hi>Kings</hi> Order, and imposes upon the <hi>King, Stephen Langton</hi> a Cardinal and the <hi>Kings</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:43770:11"/> mortal Enemy. By the way you are to understand that this <hi>Innocent</hi> was one of that blessed <hi>Tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>virate, Innocent</hi> at <hi>Rome, Saffudine</hi> the <hi>Turk</hi> at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Fratricide</hi> at <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> of wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m thus yoaked together it was said that the Prophesie of St. <hi>John</hi> was fulfilled, where the Devil was to be let loose after a Thousand Years restraint. The <hi>King</hi> gall'd to the quick with this leud and villanous Obtrusion of the <hi>Pope,</hi> so much to his dishonour, the prejudice of his <hi>Cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> and his own safety, vows to stand by his own Elect, and to die in <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Liberties</hi> of his <hi>Crown,</hi> threatning withal, that if he were cross'd in this, to hinder all Persons from crossing the Seas to <hi>Rome,</hi> and no longer to be a beggar for Forreign Justice, but <hi>Innocent</hi> slighting his Menaces, sent his commands to the <hi>English</hi> Bishops not only to submit to <hi>Langhton,</hi> but to interdict the <hi>King</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self if he continued as he called it Contumacious. Nor was the <hi>Pope</hi> more Insolent in his commands, then the Bishops officiously Disloyal and Unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to their Prince in the Execution, so that the <hi>King</hi> was deprived of the very Face of <hi>Christianity</hi> for many Years ensuing, as if not Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> but <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Apostate</hi> had mov'd up the Temples of the true God; for which Disloyalty of theirs, he made his own Dominions to hot to hold such a Disloyal Broode, confiscating their Revenues, and sending their Persons for maintenance to him that had set e'm to work: Amongst the rest, the Arch-Deacon of <hi>Norwich,</hi> for advising the <hi>Kings Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> to relinquish their Obedience to their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43770:12"/> because of the <hi>Popes Anathema,</hi> was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned and forced to wear a Coat of <hi>Lead,</hi> the weight of which sunk him in a short time to his Grave: Nor were there wanting some among the <hi>Abbots</hi> themselves, who preached that the Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the perfidious Clergy were no reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to the Prince, but due rewards of their heinous Trespasses; in regard it belonged to the <hi>King</hi> to govern and bridle the disobedience of his Subjects. Nor is there any doubt to be made, but that the <hi>King</hi> had been an easie Victor over <hi>Romes</hi> Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, had not the Nobility been envenom'd with the Clergy's infection. For notwithstanding the fiery heat of <hi>Antichristian</hi> wrath, at first he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced <hi>Ireland</hi> to Obedience, and was marching to suppress the Rebellious <hi>Welsh,</hi> but then as he was sitting at Table at <hi>Nottingham,</hi> he received intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence from his faithful friend <hi>Malcolme King</hi> of <hi>Scots</hi> and his Daughter <hi>Joan,</hi> Prince <hi>Leolins</hi> Lady, that Imminent Treason was plotted against him by sundry of his Barons, who had designed either to Murther him or betray him to the Butchery of his Foes, which dreadful Informations from such true and cordial Friends could not however fright his couragious Heart, till coming to <hi>Chester,</hi> he there understood by several other Intimations, that his Nobles had discharged themselves from his Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n which he dismissed his Army, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued the detected Conspirators, of which the three Principals flying the Land, he prosecuted their Persons, Demolished their Castles, and Confis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated their Possessions. Nevertheless they left many
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43770:12"/> more of as vile and virulent affections behind, such were those, who sent to <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France</hi> their sealed Charters, promising to settle the Crown of <hi>England</hi> on his Head, if he would come and receive it.</p>
               <p>Nor was this all, for then the Church-men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to act their parts again, and <hi>Stephen Langhton</hi> with the Bishops of <hi>Ely</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> thirsting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter revenge, though with the ruine of their <hi>Prince</hi> and Country, with loud complements sollicited their Lord the Pope, to support the <hi>English Church</hi> at the point of Ruin. Thereupon the <hi>Pope</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, that the <hi>King</hi> should be deposed, and that his Holiness should provide some other in his Rome, who to that purpose sends to <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring him to undertake the labour of Dethrown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Him, with no less reward then the Pardon of his Sins, and to enjoy the Crown of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>him</hi> and his <hi>Heirs</hi> for ever.</p>
               <p>Thereupon <hi>King Philip</hi> having this fair opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to make use of the spacious pretences of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and Devotion, not so much in obedience to the <hi>Popes</hi> command, as encouraged by the Traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous requests of the <hi>Barons,</hi> raises a vast Army, and prepares a Navy answerable for their tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sportation, in order to kill and take Possession. On the otherside <hi>King John</hi> was no less vigilant for his own defence: Nor was he yet so ill beloved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People, but that upon his Summons, such infinite Numbers flockt to <hi>Dover</hi> and the Sea Coasts there abouts, that the Officers were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to dismiss many <hi>Thousands,</hi> retaining only the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43770:13"/>
                  <hi>Choisest</hi> and most <hi>Valiant</hi> for Service, that had the leaders been but Faithful and Cordial to their Prince: There breathed not any Prince under Heaven, whose Assault <hi>England</hi> had not been able to repel.</p>
               <p>But in the midst of these preparations arrives <hi>Pandolph</hi> the <hi>Popes</hi> Legate, and in a long harangue perswades the <hi>King</hi> to submit, who at length, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of Compassion to his People, then out of any fears of his own, condescends to such conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as Necessity and the <hi>Pope,</hi> who neither of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem have any law were pleased to impose, altho much too Ignominious for so Brave and Generous a Prince, whose powerful Arms were fettered by the mistrust of his own un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aithful Nobility. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever with that little liberty which he had left him, he made a shift to ruin <hi>Philip's</hi> Fleet, upon <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphs</hi> command to forbear <hi>England,</hi> design'd upon one of the <hi>Kings Alleys,</hi> and to bring in Triumph to his own Dominions, the great preparations in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for his own Extirpation.</p>
               <p>And now the <hi>Barons</hi> break out into open di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; for when the <hi>King</hi> in prosecution of this Victory, had mustered together a <hi>Potent Army</hi> and expected at <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> that all truely <hi>English</hi> would gladly have embraced so fair an opportunity, to recover the Hereditary <hi>Provinces</hi> belonging to the <hi>Kings Dominions</hi> from the false <hi>French,</hi> his <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> restless in proclaiming their Soveraigns un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, flatly oppose themselves against his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and their Countries good, denying him both their Service and Attendance, until he were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43770:13"/> from his Excommunication. Afterwards, when the <hi>King</hi> was assoiled and hastning again to embark his Army at <hi>Portsmouth</hi> a second time, they found out new excuses to impede his designs; so that when the <hi>King</hi> had put to Sea himseif, with a small Attendance, expecting his Disloyal <hi>Barons</hi> to follow him, they all departed home, insomuch that the forsaken <hi>King</hi> was forced to return as he went. Afterwards upon the high Altar at St. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munds-bury,</hi> they swore every man severally to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their Fealty to the <hi>King,</hi> till he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descended to their specious pretences of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>In persuance of which they raise a vast Army, appointing <hi>Robert Fitz-Walter</hi> to be their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, under the Title of <hi>Martial of Gods Army and the Holy Church,</hi> and constrained the <hi>King</hi> in <hi>Running Mead</hi> near <hi>Windsor,</hi> to yeild to several <hi>Propositions</hi> altogether derogatory to his Soveraign <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and to admit Twenty Five <hi>Sel ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Peers</hi> to be sharers with him in his Government; by which means, one of the Greatest Soveraigns in Christendom was become the Twenty Sixth <hi>Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie King</hi> in his own Dominions.</p>
               <p>But as it is the fate of such Savage madness of Disloyal Dispositions, that to attain the shadow of seeming Liberties, they immerge themselves and their Abettors into bottomless Distresses, so it fair'd with these Rebellious <hi>Barons;</hi> for <hi>King John</hi> having now two Armies on Foot, the one led by himself, the other by the Earl of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously subdued thess Rebels where ever he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43770:14"/>
                  <hi>Stephen Langhton</hi> the Arch-bishop and Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader of the Conspiracy was at an Assembly in <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of <hi>Sixty one</hi> Arch bishops, <hi>four Hundred,</hi> Bishops, and <hi>eight Hundred</hi> Abbots and Priors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd and convicted of High Treason against his Natural <hi>Prince,</hi> and suspended by the <hi>Pope</hi> from his See and Dignities; the <hi>Barons</hi> were all Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated by Name, and their <hi>Poss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssions</hi> interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, so that the Rebels were now reduced to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most Despair, and therefore hopeless to find any favour from their justly offended <hi>Prince,</hi> as if the Treasons they had committed could not be safe, but by attempting greater, they call in <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>French Kings</hi> Son to their Assistance, who came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed for his own ends, and boy'd up the Rebellion for a while, but with a Resolution, if ever the Crown were setled on his Head, to have Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to perpetual Exile, all such as then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her'd to him against <hi>King John,</hi> as <hi>Traitors</hi> to their <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and to have extirpated all their <hi>Kindred</hi> in the Land. Such is the <hi>Abomination</hi> of Rebellion, even in those that make advantage of it; which being detected to them by <hi>Vincent de Melan,</hi> a Noble <hi>French-man</hi> upon his Death Bed, wrought such a Consternation among the Barons, that above forty of them prepared to prostrate themselves at the <hi>Kings</hi> Mercy; which the <hi>King</hi> was not in a Condition to receive, as lying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self upon his <hi>Deaths-Bed;</hi> but though they scaped the <hi>Kings</hi> Chastisement upon their <hi>Persons,</hi> yet was it remarkable to see how impetuously they drove on the intended punishment to themselves of their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43770:14"/> falshood to their Prince, and the due rewards laid up in store for their Disloyalty and disobedience; so that now finding to what a miserable pass they had brought themselves more afraid of their Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, they hastned to eject him out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, with the same eagerness with which they had brought him in.</p>
               <p>But as for those who obstinately adher'd to <hi>Lewis,</hi> they were most of 'em taken upon the Storm of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and in a short time found themselves at the mercy of their injured Soveraigns Son and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>HENRY</hi> III.</head>
               <p>In the Raign of this Prince we find a hot Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion raised to set up <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>French King</hi> again, by <hi>Constantine Fitz Arnulph,</hi> a Wealthy Citizen of <hi>London:</hi> But notwithstanding the numerous Rable which he had got to defend <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Title, he was at last taken and hang'd: But this was a Commotion of no great Moment, in respect of what ensued; for now <hi>Simon</hi> Earl of <hi>Leicester,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Glocester</hi> Rebels far more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and powerful gave the King new Troubles. To which purpose, having drawn into their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy several others of the Baronage, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a League against the King; and coming Arm'd to a Parliament then held at <hi>Oxford,</hi> with whom also joyned sundry of the Bishops, who had taken the same Counsels against their King, the Lords anointed, they strenuously propounded se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43770:15"/> Traiterous Articles to the King, imperiously demanding his Assent thereto, the Chief points of which were, that the King would observe their darling Charter of Liberties, and admit of such <hi>Justiciaries</hi> and great Officers as they pleased them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</p>
               <p>Then they renewed their Confederacy, solemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly swearing, that neither for Life nor Death, Love nor Hatred, they would be drawn to relent in their Trayterous purposes, till they had cleared <hi>England</hi> from their over nice and pretended fears of Aliens and Strangers. They had also a farther Project than all this, broached by the Disloyal Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops; that four and Twenty Persons should be chosen to have the sole Administration of the King and State, and the yearly appointment of great <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,</hi> reserving only to the King the Highest place at Meetings and Salutations of Honour in publick Places: To all which the King and Prince were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc'd to swear, for fear of perpetual Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the Traiterous Lords having threatened Death to all that resisted, upon which the Peers and Prelates took their Oaths to be Faithful in this their Infidelity, and the Arch-Bishops and Bishops solemnly cursed all that should Rebel against it, which impudent Treason, the Monks themselves detesting, asked with what Fore-head, especially the Prelates, durst thus impair the Kings Majesty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their sworn Fidelity to him? Which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration they prosecuted so far, that when <hi>William de Valence</hi> denyed to render up any Castle that was committed to his Charge; the Earl of <hi>Leicester</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43770:15"/> and the rest of the Conspirators replied, they would either have his Castle or his Head; And when <hi>Henry</hi> the King of the <hi>Roman's</hi> Son denied to combine with them, or to take their Oath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Fathers consent, the roundly told him, That if his Father himself would not hold with the Baronage; he should not hold a Furrow of Earth among them.</p>
               <p>On the other side, the King to vindicate his <hi>Roy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l Power</hi> out of the Usurping Barons Hands, takes the Tower of <hi>London</hi> and prepares force against force, by the help of his Brother the King of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At first the King proved successful, encounter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Enemies at <hi>Northampt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> where he took fourteen of the Principal Barons, but afterwards loosing an unfortunate Battle to the Earl of <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> was himself taken Prisoner, together with the Prince, the King of the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> his Son; By which advantage the Kingly Rebel got all the Chief Castles of the Kingdom into his Hands: But at length the Earls of <hi>Leicester</hi> and <hi>Glocester,</hi> the two main Pillars of the Rebellion, falling out about their Shares of the spoils (for what ever they pretended for the Kingdom; their own Greatness and Gain was the Chief Motive) <hi>Glocester</hi> deserts the Party of <hi>Leicester,</hi> and Asso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates with the Kings Friends, to whom after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Prince escapes out of <hi>H reford</hi> Castle; who altogether joyning Battle with the Rebels near <hi>Evesham,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Leic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ster's</hi> Army was totally routed and himself slain, his <hi>Head</hi> sent to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43770:16"/>
                  <hi>Worcester,</hi> and his <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Feet</hi> chopt off from the rest of his Body: The King being thus at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty calls a <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Winchest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> by Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of which, he seized into his <hi>Hands</hi> the <hi>Charter</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and other <hi>Towns</hi> that had sided with the Rebels: Those that were taken in the Bat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le were committed to safe Custody, and all that had taken part with the Earl were Disinherited, and a rata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble distribution made of their Estates, to the <hi>K ngs</hi> deserving Friends. The Earls two Sons were attainted, and their Mother the Countess sent out of <hi>England</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ever to return. <hi>Simon</hi> the Eldest Son of the Earl, upon his Submission, was Condemned to perpetual Exile, with only a sma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l allowance of <hi>five Hundred</hi> Marks a year for his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance. As for the Clergy, <hi>Ottobon</hi> the Popes Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Excommunicated the Bishops of <hi>Winchester, Worcester, London</hi> and <hi>Chichester,</hi> for adhering to the Rebels, and condemned the Clergy to pay their Tenths for seaven years to the King. And this was that which the Disloyal <hi>Leicester</hi> and his Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates got, instead of that <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>unjust Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> at which they aimed, for their <hi>Treason</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity</hi> to their Soveraign.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>EDWARD</hi> II.</head>
               <p>In the Raign of <hi>Edward the 2d.</hi> upon the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement</hi> of the two <hi>Spencers</hi> to the Kings favour, <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Lancast<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> and in a manner all the Barons of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as if it had been a Crime in the <hi>King</hi> to love any one but whom they pleas'd,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43770:16"/> never rested till by the Terrour of Rebellious Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Arms, they had enforced the King to banish his two favourites.</p>
               <p>Thereupon the <hi>King</hi> manfully resolving to die in the quarrel, or bring his Lords to be at his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posal, levies an Army, marches to <hi>Cicester,</hi> taking many Castles and beseiging others.</p>
               <p>This put the Barons into such a Consternation, that many of them deserted their Chieftain the Earl of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> and rendred themselves to the Kings Mercy. Others were apprehended, as were the two <hi>Mortimers;</hi> the rest sent to <hi>Walling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Castle. However the Faction, tho weaken'd by these defections, made head in the North un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Earl of <hi>Lancaster:</hi> Thither the <hi>King</hi> march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and with the only shew of his Army made the Earl fly to <hi>Burton</hi> upon <hi>Trent.</hi> Nor did the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spleasure of <hi>Heaven,</hi> nor the revenging <hi>Arm</hi> of Soveraign Power leave them so; for at <hi>Borrough-bridge Humfrey de Bohun,</hi> one of the Chief Rebels was slain by a <hi>Welshman,</hi> who thrust him from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Bridge into his Body with his <hi>Spear.</hi> The Earl of <hi>Lancaster</hi> also, with other Principal Barons and Knights, to the number of Fourscore and ten were also taken <hi>Prisoners,</hi> by Persons of no great Note, the Captains of <hi>Carleil</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> who with considerable forces out of those parts, stopt the farther <hi>Progress</hi> of the Rebels at <hi>Borrough-bridg</hi> already mentioned.</p>
               <p>The Earl of <hi>Lancaster</hi> with five or six Barons more were beheaded at <hi>Pontfraict.</hi> The Lords <hi>Clifford, Mowbray</hi> and <hi>Dey-vil</hi> were hanged in Iron
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43770:17"/> Chains at <hi>York;</hi> the Lord <hi>Badlesmore</hi> was Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and others in other places, as the Lord <hi>John Clifford</hi> at <hi>Glocester,</hi> the Lord <hi>Henry Teys</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> and at <hi>VVindsor</hi> the Lord <hi>Francis de Aldenham;</hi> all which miserable Tragedies were only the <hi>dire Effects</hi> of <hi>Disloyalty</hi> and <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>True it is, that this unfortunate <hi>Prince</hi> was depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the revengful Contrivances of a <hi>Disloyal Wife</hi> overswayed and governed by the most <hi>Ambitious</hi> and vindicative Rebel then alive, <hi>Roger</hi> Lord <hi>Mortimer.</hi> But <hi>Heaven</hi> would not permit that either should long enjoy the Fruits of that dismal Tragedy which they had acted: For <hi>Mortimer</hi> when he least suspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted it, was ravished by the Young King from the Embraces of his <hi>Adulterous Moth r,</hi> and ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niously hanged at the common Gallows at <hi>Tiborn.</hi> The Queen Mother was deprived of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er <hi>Ample Dower,</hi> confined within the streight Limits of a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row aboad at <hi>Risings</hi> near <hi>London,</hi> put to a short <hi>Pension</hi> and <hi>Allowance</hi> of only a thousand <hi>Pounds per annum,</hi> upon which she liv'd a solitary Widow for thirty Years together, debarred of all those <hi>Pomps</hi> and <hi>Honours,</hi> otherwise due to her high <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Quality.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>RICHARD</hi> II.</head>
               <p>Hitherto we have seen the <hi>Disloyalty</hi> and <hi>Disobedience</hi> of the most <hi>Eminent Personages</hi> of the Nation severely punished by the Revenging <hi>Hand</hi> of <hi>Providence:</hi> In this Kings Reign, the rabble would needs undertake to be the Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43770:17"/> and like a <hi>Monstrous Hydra,</hi> erecting their shapeless heads, began to hiss against their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns <hi>Regal Power</hi> and <hi>Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Prince</hi> coming young to the Crown, had appointed for his Governour <hi>John D.</hi> of <hi>Lancaster</hi> the <hi>Kings Uncle,</hi> who also assumed the Titles of King of <hi>Castle</hi> and <hi>Leon;</hi> whose Government not pleasing the <hi>People,</hi> by reason of a Tax Levied by <hi>Poll</hi> upon all <hi>Persons</hi> above sixteen Years of <hi>Age,</hi> moved the enraged Multitude to roul together in such a dreadful Torrent, that the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, seemed as it were suddainly fallen under their most wicked fury.</p>
               <p>There were in this rebellious Insurrection, the Commons and Peasants, principally those of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Essex,</hi> who drew into their Infernal <hi>Associati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> the Neighbouring Countries of <hi>Suffolk, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk, Cambridg, Surrey, Kent</hi> and other places.</p>
               <p>They of <hi>Kent</hi> embattel'd themselves under two Banners of St. <hi>George,</hi> and threescore and ten di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>splayed <hi>Engsigns,</hi> upon <hi>Black Heath,</hi> and from thence came to <hi>London,</hi> where the Generality of the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> inclining to them, they became Masters of Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule, and burnt the <hi>Priory</hi> of St. <hi>Johns,</hi> and the Magnificent <hi>Palace</hi> of the <hi>Savoy</hi> then belonging to the D. of <hi>Lancaster;</hi> with all the Riches in it; and all this in a kind of <hi>Holy Outrage,</hi> throwing one of their Fellows into the flame, for having thrust a piece of stollen <hi>Plate</hi> into his Bosom, like another <hi>Achan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Rebels of <hi>Essex</hi> marched to <hi>Lamb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th,</hi> where they burnt all the <hi>Archbishops</hi> Goods, and defaced
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43770:18"/> all the Writings, Records, Rowles and Monuments of the Chancery; Nor was their desperate fury satisfyed to extend it self to the spoyl of <hi>Houses</hi> and <hi>Substance;</hi> they laid bloody hands also upon the most eminent and worthy personages in the <hi>Kingdom, Simon Tibald</hi> Arch-bishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Hales</hi> Lord Prior of <hi>St. J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hns</hi> and Treasurer of <hi>England,</hi> whom without respect to the Majestie of the <hi>King,</hi> or the priviledge of their <hi>Honourable Dignities,</hi> they most inhumanly murdered by cutting off their <hi>Heads</hi> upon <hi>To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er-Hill,</hi> in the midst of their Infernal shouts and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Yels.</p>
               <p>They had many Captains to lead them on and encourage them in their Mischievous Enterprizes, of which the chief were <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> of <hi>Maidstone,</hi> and <hi>Jack Straw;</hi> They had besides a Chaplain as Graceless as themselves, one <hi>John Ball</hi> an Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated Priest, who with his precious Doctrine nourish't their enflamed Rage, and their Number was esteemed at one time to have been a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thousand. Of these a great Number accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Kings Mercy, returned home, but then <hi>VVat Tyler</hi> nothing dismayed, but rather beleiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself now surrounded with a more despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and resolved party, who having refused the <hi>Kings</hi> Pardon, were bound to adhere to him in his Disloyalty, under pretence of disliking the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles tendered to him by the <hi>King,</hi> sought to win time, till he might put in Execution his intended execrable Treasons, which were to murder the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Great Men</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and to Erect
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43770:18"/> Petty Tyrannies to themselves in every <hi>Shire.</hi> In <hi>Norfolk</hi> also one <hi>John Littistar</hi> a Dyer, had taken upon him the Title of <hi>King of the Commons,</hi> and in <hi>Suffolk</hi> one <hi>John VVraw</hi> another leud Priest, had assigned the same Dignity to one <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hn VVest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Young King in these fears and dangers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired to <hi>VVestminster,</hi> while <hi>VVat Tyler</hi> with his Camp of <hi>Rakeshames</hi> attended in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> still caviling with the conditions of Peace, till the <hi>King</hi> arriving from <hi>VVestminster,</hi> placed himself on <hi>Hors<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>back</hi> before St. <hi>Bartholomews</hi> Gate, attended by <hi>Walworth</hi> Lord Mayor of the City, and others of high place and quality, and from thence sent for the Lordly Rebel to come and speak with him. Nor was it without great entreaty that the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful Mushrome vouchsaf'd to come, and when he came behaved himself so insolently, that he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to Murder Sir <hi>John Newton</hi> for his Omission of some Punctillio of Respect, which he arrogated to his Usurped Dignity, upon which he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently with a drawn Sword arrested by <hi>Walworth,</hi> who followed his blows with that success, that the new Prodigie of a Traytor was soon fell'd to the ground and slain, only pitied in this, that his fall was by an Honourable <hi>Arm,</hi> and not by the <hi>Hand</hi> of the Common Executioner.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Rable</hi> seeing the fall of their Captain, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for extremity of <hi>Revenge,</hi> at what time the young <hi>King</hi> with a present Wit and Courage spur'd forth his <hi>Horse,</hi> and bid the mutinous Throng fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him without being grieved for the loss of a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43770:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:43770:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:43770:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:43770:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:43770:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:43770:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:43770:22"/>
                  <hi>Ribauld</hi> and <hi>Traytor,</hi> for that he would be their Captain, upon which the Multitude not daring to lift up a <hi>Hand</hi> against him (such is the awe of real Majestie) pressed after him into the Field, belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themselves now sure of their desires. In the mean while the Lord Mayor slips into the City, Arms immediately a thousand stout Citizens, and with <hi>Tyler's Head</hi> born before them, speeds to the Kings relief.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Rebels</hi> now seeing themselves hem'd in with Armed Men, some fled, some fell upon their knees, and answerably to their baseness beg'd their lives, who lately thought themselves both Masters of the Field, and of the <hi>King</hi> himself.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Norfolk, Henry de Spencer</hi> Bishop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, making use of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Sword, flew into the <hi>Rebels Trenches,</hi> and after he had slain a great number of the Disloyal Croud, caused their Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shroom <hi>King Littestar,</hi> to be drawn and hang'd, and then to have his <hi>Head</hi> chopt off.</p>
               <p>Into <hi>Essex</hi> the Lord <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Woodstock</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> Uncle, with Sir <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> were sent, where the <hi>Rebels</hi> were strong in Number, they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless broken at the very first charge made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
               <p>The same <hi>Fortune</hi> attended them in all other parts where they had embody'd; so that at length being all quell'd and dissipated, nothing remained but the deserved punishment of their detested Insolence; for which about 15 hundred were Executed in several places. And this end for the present had these Infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43770:22"/> Attempts of the baser People, in which was plainly to be beheld the hideous Face of <hi>Anarchie</hi> and <hi>Plebeian Rage,</hi> which tho' it be violent for the time, yet seldome proves durable, still melting at the Approach of over-awing <hi>Majesty;</hi> it being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, That the heat of this popular Fury did not last above eight days.</p>
               <p>But to shew that the People are only like good <hi>Tools,</hi> altogether ineffectual unless in the hands of them that know how to make use of them, the ensuing <hi>Rebellion</hi> of the <hi>Lords,</hi> was an apparent Argument: For tho they could not manage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, yet being in the hands of them that knew how to make advantage of their Discontents, and their Robustious Numbers, they wrought that mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief to their Soveraign as sturdy Instruments, which they could not effect by their <hi>Impolitick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances.</hi> Nor were the Discontented Lords neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent to lay hold of the Opportunity, while they were in this floating Humour.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Ireland,</hi> whom the <hi>King</hi> most Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially lov'd, for that very reason was become a great Eye-sore to several of the Nobility, but more especially to the Duke of <hi>Glocester,</hi> one of the Kings Uncles; for that the Duke of <hi>Ireland</hi> had Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diated his Wife near Kins-woman to the <hi>King</hi> and him, and had taken to his Bed one of the <hi>Queens</hi> Women, a <hi>Bohemian</hi> of mean Birth.</p>
               <p>This Injury to his Kins-woman boyl'd in <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> Stomach, and therefore under the pretence of <hi>Reformation,</hi> and removing <hi>Evil Counsellors,</hi> he Confederates with the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:43770:23"/> the Earls of <hi>Arundel, Warwick, Marshal,</hi> and others at <hi>Arundel</hi> in <hi>Essex,</hi> where they also take an Oath of <hi>Secresie,</hi> and conclude to raise a Power against the <hi>King</hi> to obtain what they aim'd at, not <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but <hi>Revenge,</hi> and the Mastery of their <hi>Gentle Soveraign,</hi> by main force.</p>
               <p>This Conspiracy was Discovered by <hi>Thomas Mowbray</hi> Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> a Party in the <hi>Plot</hi> to the <hi>King;</hi> upon which the Duke of <hi>Glocester</hi> was surprized by <hi>Mowbray,</hi> who waited for him in the Woods thorough which he was to pass, and sent Prisoner to <hi>Callis.</hi> The Earls of <hi>Arundel</hi> and <hi>Warwick,</hi> with the Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Cheney,</hi> were likewise Arrested, and Committed to safe Custody. And now what was the Fruits of this Topping piece of Disloyalty, hatch'd by these Personages of such eminent degree? The Earls of <hi>Arundel</hi> and <hi>Warwick</hi> Convicted before the Duke of <hi>Lancaster, Lord High Steward</hi> for their Tryals, for the <hi>Treasons</hi> already Rehears'd: the former lost his Head, and the other was Banish'd to the <hi>Isle of Man,</hi> though under the same Sentence of Condemnation. The Duke of <hi>Glocester</hi> was put to Death at <hi>Callis,</hi> being too much the Darling of the unruly Multitude to be brought to publick Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice. As for those that were his Favourites, by their ill-Counsels and worse management of Affairs, betray'd him to his Deposal; they, for their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sloyalty to his Successour, had their Portion of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity in the next <hi>King</hi>'s Reign.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43770:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>HENRY</hi> IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, while Duke of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made his claim to the Crown, it was by all the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>K ngdom</hi> with one consent grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That the said <hi>Lord Duke</hi> should Reign over them: and thereupon he was first placed in the <hi>Royal Throne</hi> by the Arch-bishops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> and afterwards solemnly Crowned and Anointed at <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stminster,</hi> which certainly invested him in all the Prerogatives of an <hi>English Monarch,</hi> and thereby the Fealty and Homage of all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects became due to him.</p>
               <p>But scarce was he warm in his new Atchiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Soveraignty, when a Nes;t of powerful Enemies began to hatch his Destruction under the shadow of his own Wings. The chief in the Conspiracy, were the Earls of <hi>Huntington, Rutland, Kent,</hi> and <hi>Salisbury,</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Carl sle,</hi> and several others of great Quality. The main Point of the Plot was to Kill the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Son,</hi> and to restore depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <hi>Richard;</hi> But the <hi>Plot</hi> was Discovered first by the Earl of <hi>Rutland,</hi> and then by the <hi>Lord Mayor:</hi> tho' with so short a warning, that the <hi>King</hi> was scarce out of danger, when the Earls of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Salisbury</hi> entred <hi>Windsor Castle</hi> with four hundred Men, with a Resolution to have seized upon the <hi>K ng.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The two <hi>Lords</hi> having thus missed their Prey, Marched away to <hi>Wallingford,</hi> thence to <hi>Abington,</hi> and so to <hi>Circester,</hi> giving out as they went, That <hi>King Richard</hi> was at Liberty, and at <hi>Pontfract,</hi> at the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43770:24"/> Head of a hundred thousand Men. But this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port not taking with the People, they suborn'd one <hi>Maunden,</hi> who had b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en one of <hi>Richards</hi> Chaplains, very like him in Features and Complexion, to take upon him the person of the <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Event was not answerable to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; for the <hi>Townsm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> of <hi>Cicest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> fell upon the two Earls with that Vigour, That they took 'em both Prisoners; and seeing their Town on Fire, which was procured by some of the <hi>Lords Followers,</hi> the better to rescue them again, while the people were busied in the quenching the Flames, they imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately hal'd their Noble Prisoners forth, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out more delay, according to the Method of <hi>Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Justice,</hi> sever'd their Heads from their Bodies. The Earl of <hi>Huntington</hi> was Apprehended in <hi>Essex,</hi> and Beheaded at <hi>Pleshie,</hi> at the Instigation of the Widow of the late Duke of <hi>Glocester,</hi> put to Death at <hi>Callis</hi> by <hi>Richard.</hi> The Lord <hi>Spencer</hi> had the like Execution done upon him at <hi>Bristol:</hi> and <hi>Maunden</hi> the <hi>Counterfeit Richard,</hi> was Drawn, Hang'd, and Headed; there being no less then Nineteen in all that were put to Death for this Conspiracy, only the Bishop of <hi>Carlisle</hi> was preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved alive by the Kings Clemency after Sentence of Condemnation. So far was <hi>Heaven</hi> from being propitious to Subjects in their Officious intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the Rights of Crowned Princes, who when once they come to be anointed, are the <hi>Sacred Wards</hi> and <hi>Pupils</hi> of God himself. Nor would God permit those rash Attempters against their <hi>Reigning Monarch</hi> to <hi>regain,</hi> what their former
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43770:24"/> Prince had been forced to lose and resign, through their unfaithful Conduct of his <hi>Prosperiy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Several other Conspiracies there were of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of meaner Rank, which being Discovered (as all <hi>Cland<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stine Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acheries generally</hi> are) the first that fell under the <hi>Kings Justice</hi> was a <hi>Priest</hi> of <hi>Ware,</hi> who was <hi>Drawn</hi> and <hi>Hang'd;</hi> the same fate befel <hi>Walter Baldock Prior</hi> of <hi>Lawnd.</hi> A <hi>Fryer Minorite</hi> was likewise for concealment <hi>Hang'd</hi> in his <hi>Fryers Weeds;</hi> and not long after eight <hi>Franciscans</hi> for the same Confederacy ended their Days by the hand of the <hi>Common Executioner:</hi> as also did Sir <hi>Roger Clar nden,</hi> Reputed to be the Natural Son of the <hi>Black Prince.</hi> For the <hi>King</hi> being endanger'd in the Main, resolved to spare none upon whom the Crime or Concealment was found.</p>
               <p>But if these had any pretence or colour while deposed <hi>Richard</hi> was yet alive, yet the <hi>Fiery Hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spur,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Northumberland</hi>'s Son, and the Earl of <hi>Worcester</hi> his Fathers Brother after <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi>'s Decease, could alledge no excuse for those fatal <hi>Animosities</hi> which Armed them against their Sovereign, to both their Confusions.</p>
               <p>However, the colourable causes of their taking Armes, were the usual <hi>Paintings</hi> and <hi>Flourishes</hi> that set off such Attempts, the great care of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths Reformation,</hi> and their own safety. But the <hi>Kernel</hi> of their Design was, to thrust <hi>Henry</hi> out of his Seat, and deprive him of his Life, and then to advance the Title of <hi>Mortimer, Earl of March,</hi> their nearest Kins-man. To this purpose, <hi>Pierce, Mortimer,</hi> and <hi>Owen Glendour</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43770:25"/> entred into a Triple Confederacy, and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> between them, Young <hi>Hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spur</hi> first makes Head about <hi>Chester</hi> and the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> to whom with the privity of his Father, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired the Old Earl of <hi>Worcester,</hi> leaving the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Young Prince and his Houshold, over which the <hi>King</hi> had placed him.</p>
               <p>On the other side the <hi>Kings Armies</hi> with all speed, and with the Prince his Son, Guarded by a considerable Force, advances towards <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> before which Town <hi>Hotspur</hi> was sat down, and just ready to give the Assault; when the <hi>Royal Standard</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing Discovered, he was forc'd to draw off from that Enterprize, so that now he thought of nothing more then to Embattle his <hi>Army,</hi> consisting of fourteen thousand strong and hardy Blades, to try the Fortune of War against an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Souldier.</p>
               <p>Nevertheless Peace was offer'd and had ensu'd, but that the mischievous Earl of <hi>Worcester,</hi> by misreporting and falsifying his Sovereigns words, precipated his <hi>Nephew</hi> into suddain Battle.</p>
               <p>The Kings Courage was not small in the Fight, as neither was the Danger: The Young Prince of <hi>VVales</hi> being Wounded with an Arrow in the Face, the Lord <hi>Piercy,</hi> and Earl <hi>Douglass,</hi> then whom it is said, That the wide World had not two greater Champions, instead of spending them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves upon the Multitude, bent all their fierceness upon the King, in whose Person they were sure ten thousand fell. With this Resolution they most furiously rush'd forward with their Spears and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43770:25"/> Swords, but the Earl of <hi>Dunbar</hi> discovering their purpose, drew the King from the place which he had design'd to make good, and thereby in likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood sav'd his Life; for the <hi>Standard</hi> was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, the <hi>Standard</hi> Bearer slain, and ten other Knights Fighting to defend the <hi>Standard,</hi> all mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally Wounded: besides that, <hi>Douglass</hi> with his own hand slew three that day that were severally in the <hi>Kings Coat-Armour,</hi> so that many thought that the King had been kill'd, and ran out of the Field.</p>
               <p>Thus lasted a most obstinate and bloody Contest between a Sovereign and his Rebellious Subjects for above three hours, till at length <hi>Hotspur</hi> still Riding in the Head of the Battle in contempt of <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Danger</hi> met with his match, and was slain by an unknown hand, with whose fall the Courages of all the rest fell into their Feet, of which they made the speediest use they could to save themselves.</p>
               <p>Rebellion and Disloyalty thus vanquished in the Field, and Treason having by Providence lost her chief support, the Earl of <hi>VVorcester,</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Vernan,</hi> and the <hi>Baron</hi> of <hi>Kinderton,</hi> three of the most eminent Rebels, had their Heads chopt off the next day but one after the Battle; And as for the Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> though his Life was pardoned, yet his Revenues were Confiscated, and himself reduced to a Pension of Necessary Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which (however) the King, when he had sufficiently humbled him, out of a particular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and compassion toward him, restored him
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43770:26"/> afterwards in Parliament, all which nevertheless did not save his <hi>Head</hi> at the long run.</p>
               <p>No sooner was this <hi>Rebellion</hi> thus appeased, but <hi>Tho. Mowbray, E. Marshal,</hi> disliking it seems the Carriage of publick matters, draws <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chard le Scroope</hi> Arch-bishop of <hi>York</hi> into a new Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, in full hope that the Erl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> the Lord <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdolph,</hi> the Citizens of <hi>York</hi> and the common People would assist their Cause, which was glossed with the usual specious pretence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressing publick abuses. The Earl of <hi>Westmore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hearing of this Attempt, gathers a force to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to encounter 'em, but perceiving himself too feeble, he betakes himself to stratagem, and by feigning to Embrace the Quarrel got both the Ring-leaders into his own Power, and presented them as an acceptable Oblation to the King, who Sacrificed the Traiterous Heads both of the Earl and the Arch-bishop, to his just Anger. Which done, the King pursued the Earl of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland,</hi> who notwithstanding all his late fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours was relapsed again into his former Disloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and the Lord <hi>Bardolph,</hi> and forced them both to take Sanctuarie in <hi>Scotland,</hi> with the loss of his Castles and Mannors, which the King seized a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time into his own <hi>Hands.</hi> The said Earl and Lord, not long after endeavouring to raise new stirs in the North of <hi>England,</hi> were encountered by the Sheriff of <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> at what time the Earl was slain out right, and the Lord <hi>Bardolph</hi> mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally wounded. The Head of the Earl was chopt from his dead Body, and being ignominiously car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43770:26"/> through the City of <hi>London,</hi> was fixed upon <hi>London Bridge,</hi> so difficult a thing it is for Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to be assured of rest and quiet in their Graves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>HENRY</hi> V.</head>
               <p>This Warlike and Renowned Prince found so much Employment abroad for the Active Spirits of his Fiery Nobles, that open Rebellion had no leisure to set on foot the Intreagues of Disloyal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance, only the Reign of this most vertuous Prince affords one Remarkable Example of Divine Justice, upon the most detestable and inhumane Machinations against a Soveraign Princes so little deserving such ill usage, that ever could harbour in the breast of Men pretending to Honour and High Birth. For the King of <hi>France</hi> having tryed all ways to divert the Storm that threatned his <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions</hi> from the <hi>English Invasion,</hi> and every way frustrated in his Expectations, at length sent over a Million of Gold to the Earl of <hi>Camb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idge,</hi> the Lord <hi>Scroop</hi> and <hi>Grey,</hi> all three at that time in special favour with the King, either to betray <hi>Henry</hi> into his Hands, or to Murder him before he could arrive in <hi>Normandy.</hi> These persons unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily tempted with such a Golden bait, to make their Faction the stronger, though <hi>Scroop</hi> was Lord <hi>Treasurer, Grey</hi> a <hi>Privy Councellour,</hi> and <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg</hi> Son of <hi>Edmund</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> meant to draw in <hi>Edmund</hi> Earl of <hi>March,</hi> the Heir to <hi>Lio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel D.</hi> of <hi>Clarence,</hi> and the next in Succession of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43770:27"/> House of <hi>York,</hi> and revealing to him their intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed purposed, enforced him to swear to their Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, which if he refused they threatened his <hi>Death;</hi> whereupon the <hi>Duke</hi> required but an hours Respite which being with great difficulty granted, he went to the King and revealed the Conspiracy but the <hi>Night</hi> before the <hi>Day</hi> that the King intended to put to Sea.</p>
               <p>Upon which the Parties being apprehended and brought before the King, in the presence of many of the Nobility, the Magnanimous <hi>Henry</hi> thus spake. <q>With what Horror O Lord, may any true <hi>English Heart</hi> consider, that you for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of a Forraign <hi>Enemy,</hi> should imbrue your Hands in our Blood, as also in the Blood of our Brethren to the ruin of your Native Soil! Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge herein though I seek not, yet for the safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of you my dear Friends, and for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of the Realm, I am by Place and Office to Minister a remedy against these Offencers. Then addressing himself to the three <hi>Traytors,</hi> Get ye hence therefore, said <hi>He,</hi> Miserable Wretches, and receive the just reward of your <hi>Deserts,</hi> wherein God give you Repentance for your so foul Crimes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>After which they were all three upon a legal Tryal and Conviction, beheaded at <hi>Southampton,</hi> to their <hi>Eternal Infamy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:43770:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>HENRY</hi> VI.</head>
               <p>Truly might this Prince be called a Prince of Peace, had not the Title which he held, requiring se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verily and Prowess, not Meekness and Devotion, to defend it, involved him in the most ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nous Wars that ever afflicted <hi>England;</hi> for now the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>York</hi> resuming fresh hopes from the weakness of a Young, Gentle and Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gious Soveraign, lays the Foundations of bloody Designs and dismal Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, nor was it the meanest of their Projects to sow the Seeds of <hi>Disloyalty</hi> and <hi>Dis bedience</hi> among the People, who were to be the Instruments and Tools for the Master Workmen to make use of. For the heat of Faction, as the preternatural and sultry heats of Summer, engender infectious A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimals and Insects to fill the Air with their Conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, produces those popular Tumults, that no less molest the quiet State of Kingdoms; and this Factious <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at</hi> it was that begot that pestiferous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection in this Kings Reign, under the Insolent and Hair-brain'd Conduct, if I may so call it of <hi>Cade</hi> and his followers, so pernicious to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weal, though more ruinous to the Authors.</p>
               <p>Hence it came to pass, that the Commons of <hi>Kent,</hi> cherished and emboldened by persons of high Quality and Contrivance, took Arms against their Soveraign. They were headed by one <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> who had been <hi>Servant</hi> to <hi>Sir Thomas Dacre</hi> a <hi>Sussex</hi> Gentleman: But having killed a Woman with Child, he was forced to abjure the Land, and to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43770:28"/> turn <hi>French,</hi> to whom he swore <hi>Service.</hi> But now returning, he is the Instrument to hang out <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timers</hi> Name, like a displayed <hi>Ensign,</hi> to draw a party, feigning to be Cousin to the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>York:</hi> This <hi>Cade,</hi> whom others call <hi>John Mendal,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>John Merral,</hi> having drawn great Numbers to follow him, encamped at <hi>Black-Heath,</hi> and in his Writings called himself the <hi>Captain of Kent.</hi> His pretences, like those of all <hi>Disloyal Actions</hi> were the common good, with others of the same alluring strain. But his particular demands were;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>Richard Duke of York</hi> should be sent for out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and with others, whose Names were only set down for Stales and Colour, be principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly used in Council.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Authors of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Glocesters</hi> death might be brought to Condign Punishment.</p>
               <p>Thus Traiterously to the Kings Welfare, and scandalously to the Kings gentle Government did this arrogant Traytor pretend to write to his <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign.</hi> The King moved with the Indignitie and Danger of these bravely advances with an Army toward the Rebels, upon which their Captain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires with his Rabble to <hi>Sennock</hi> in the same Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; the King supposing he had fled, sends after him <hi>Sir Humfrey Stafford</hi> with some forces: But <hi>Cade</hi> made a bold halt at <hi>Sennock,</hi> and after a long fight slew <hi>Sir Humfrey</hi> with several others, and then armed himself in the slain Knights habil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and wore his guilt <hi>Spurs.</hi> The King and Queen having Intelligence of this Misfortune,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43770:28"/> leave the Tower of <hi>London</hi> in the Custody of the Lord <hi>Scales,</hi> and one <hi>Matthew Gough</hi> a famous Souldier, and the City to the Fidelity of the Lord Mayor, departing themselves for <hi>Kenelworth.</hi> However the <hi>Head-long</hi> Vulgar of <hi>London</hi> favouring the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, gave them Entrance within the Walls, where the Arch-Traytor took upon him to fine one of the Aldermen <hi>five Hundred</hi> Marks, for proposing to make resistance. At the same time also the <hi>Essex Men</hi> were encamped upon <hi>Mile-end Green,</hi> equally involv'd in the same <hi>Disloyalty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cade</hi> thus admitted into the City, as he March'd thorough <hi>Canon-street</hi> struck his hand upon <hi>London-Stone,</hi> crying out, <hi>Now is</hi> Mortimer <hi>Lord of this City.</hi> And then proceeding to act the Tyrants Part, sends for the <hi>Lord Say,</hi> Treasurer of <hi>England,</hi> Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Tower</hi> by the <hi>King,</hi> a little before his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, at the Instigation of his worst Adviser, and caus'd that Noble Gentleman to be Beheaded in <hi>Cheap-side,</hi> and his Body to be cut into Quarters; by which loss of so trusty and grave a Person, the <hi>King</hi>'s Party was not a little weaken'd.</p>
               <p>The next <hi>Tragedy</hi> was <hi>Crom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re</hi>'s, the <hi>High She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> and Son in-Law to the said Lady, who was drag'd out of the <hi>Fleet,</hi> and had his Head Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed upon <hi>Mile-end-Green,</hi> to atone the <hi>Essex Rebells,</hi> without any Tryal or Ceremony of Law. The <hi>Major,</hi> and wiser wealthy Citizens, over-rul'd by <hi>Faction</hi> till then, grow now apprehensive of their danger, and secretly send to the <hi>Lord Scales</hi> for aid, who sends <hi>Matthew Gough</hi> to their assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; upon which the <hi>Kentish Men</hi> ran furiously
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43770:29"/> to their Armes, seeing their entrance into the City was barr'd, for they us'd every Night to retreat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Southwark,</hi> where their Captain had taken up his head Quarters. <hi>Cade</hi> therefore endeavours to open his passage by force, but in spight of all his power, the Citizens made good the Bridge against him, though w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th the loss of <hi>Gough</hi> himself, and several others.</p>
               <p>At length to put a quick-end to their miseries, Impunity is proclaim'd for all of Offenders, and sent to the <hi>Rebels</hi> in the <hi>King</hi>'s Name by the <hi>Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury, Lord-Chancellor</hi> under the <hi>Great-Seal</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> upon which assurance of their safeties the <hi>Rebels</hi> disperse, and leave their <hi>Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Impostour</hi> in the <hi>Sudds.</hi> It was time then for <hi>Cade</hi> to seek for shelter; but upon a sum of Money set upon his Head for any one that should kill or take the <hi>Counterfeit Mortimer,</hi> he was at length discover'd, and slain by one <hi>Alexander Eden,</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Kent.</hi> After which, his Carcass was brought up to <hi>London,</hi> where he had the <hi>Honour</hi> to have his <hi>Head</hi> set <hi>Sentinel</hi> upon <hi>London-bridge,</hi> and his Quarters advanced in several parts of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, where he was laying the Sandy Foundations of his vainly fancy'd future <hi>Grandeur.</hi> Some six and twenty more also fell by the stroke of <hi>Justice</hi> for a terror to the rest, who now Conscious of their Crimes, where they had revel'd in <hi>Disloyalty</hi> before, came to <hi>Black Heath</hi> in their Shirts, to implore the <hi>King</hi>'s mercy: who satisfyed with the punishment of the <hi>Ringleaders,</hi> was easily induc'd to pardon the submissive.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:43770:29"/>
               <p>Nor may it be omitted, That the Duke of <hi>Busk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham,</hi> by whose popular sway in the Nation, <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the Third advanced himself to the Crown, by shedding the Blood of so many <hi>Innocent Peers,</hi> and the Murder of the <hi>Lawful Heirs,</hi> at all which vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Proceedings the Duke most <hi>Trayterously</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niv'd, was the first who revolting from <hi>Richard,</hi> after he was become his Sovereign, who being him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self betray'd by his own Servant, whose Fortunes he had particularly raised, that fell a Sacrifice to <hi>Richard's</hi> revenge for confederating with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Ely</hi> and others, to restore the <hi>Lancastrian</hi> Line, being Beheaded without any Legal Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or Form of Justice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>HENRY</hi> VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry the Seventh,</hi> as a Prince that had been vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious in Battle, and at the beginning of his Reign had prevailed with the Parliament in what ever he desired, and had the ring of the Peoples acclamation still in his Ears, thought the rest of his Reign would have been but a Play, and the meer <hi>enjoying</hi> of a <hi>Kingdom.</hi> But he did much overcast his Fortunes, which for many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prov'd full of broken Seas and Tempests. For e're he was hardly warm in his Government, as he was taking a Progress to visit and settle the North parts of <hi>England,</hi> he was no sooner arrived at <hi>Lincoln,</hi> but he received Intelligence that the Lord <hi>Lovel</hi> and the two <hi>Staffords</hi> were escaped out of Sanctuary, no body could tell whether; which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43770:30"/> Advertisement the King at first despised and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his Journey to <hi>York,</hi> but when he was come thither; he received fresh <hi>News</hi> that <hi>Lovel</hi> was at <hi>Hand</hi> with a great <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> and that the <hi>Staffords</hi> were in <hi>Arms</hi> in <hi>Worcestershire,</hi> and were preparing to Assail the City of <hi>Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cester</hi> it self. Upon this the <hi>King</hi> fends a force of <hi>three Thous nd Men,</hi> under the Conduct of the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Bedford,</hi> against the Chief Rebel the Lord <hi>Lovel,</hi> giving Commission however to the <hi>Duke,</hi> to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim his pardon to all that would come in, which fell out as the <hi>King</hi> Expected. For upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of Pardon, the Lord <hi>Lovel</hi> mistrusting his own followers fled away into <hi>Lancashire,</hi> and from thence into <hi>Flanders</hi> to the Lady <hi>Margaret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The two <hi>Staffords</hi> and their forces hearing what had happened to the Lord <hi>Lovel,</hi> despaired and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spersed: But being both taken out of Sanctuary, which was then thought to be no sufficient Refuge for Rebels, the <hi>Elder Brother</hi> was Executed at <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> and the <hi>Younger Brother</hi> as being seduced by the <hi>Elder</hi> Brother received his Pardon. And this was the disastrous Event of the first Rebellion hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening in this Kings <hi>Reign;</hi> which might have been a sufficient warning to others, but that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> is a Monster that has neither <hi>Eyes</hi> nor <hi>Ears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his second year was acted that famous <hi>Farce</hi> of <hi>Lambert Simnel,</hi> which cost him a second Push for his <hi>Royal Diadem,</hi> before he could pull the Idol down.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Lambert Simnel</hi> was a Bakers Son of the Age of <hi>fifteen Years,</hi> a well Favoured and Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43770:30"/>
                  <hi>Youth,</hi> and one who had something of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Dignity and Grace, fulness of Aspect in his Countenance. This <hi>You<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> living in <hi>Oxford,</hi> under the tuition of <hi>Richard Simon</hi> a suttle Priest, it came into the Priest<hi>'s</hi> mind, hearing what Men talked abroad, to cause this Lad to Conterfeit and Personate the second Son of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>fourth,</hi> supposed to be murthered in the <hi>Tower;</hi> but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards changed his mind, to take upon him the Person of the Lord <hi>Edward Plantagen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t</hi> then Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the <hi>Tower,</hi> with great Pains and Industry instructed him in the part which he was to Act.</p>
               <p>But because he doubted there would be too near looking, and too near a prospective into his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guise, if he should display his Counterfeit in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he thought it more convenient at a distance, and therefore sailed with his <hi>Scholar</hi> into <hi>Ireland,</hi> where the affection to the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>York</hi> was most in Height.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simons</hi> first Address was to the Lord <hi>Fitz Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard,</hi> Earl of <hi>Kildare</hi> and Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whose Eyes he cast such a Mist, by force of his own Insinuation and the Carriage of his Pupil, who expressed a perfect natural Princely behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, as left him fully possessed that it was the true <hi>Plantagenet.</hi> The Earl presently communicated the matter with some of the Nobles and others at first secretly, but finding them equally affected with himself, he suffered the business to take Air and vent it self abroad, on purpose to taste the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of the People, who if the great ones were in a forwardness, were themselves all in a fury, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43770:31"/> this same Airy <hi>Phantosme</hi> with an Incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Observance; so that with marvellous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent and Applause this <hi>Counterfeit Plantagenet</hi> was brought with great Solemnity to the Castle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and there saluted, serened and honoured as a King, all Allegiance to <hi>King Henry</hi> being laid aside: And within a few days after, he was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed <hi>King</hi> in <hi>Dublin,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Edward the sixth,</hi> there being not so much as a Sword all this while drawn in King <hi>Henry's</hi> Quarrel.</p>
               <p>Upon this the King summons his Counsel toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and upon Mature deliberation, suspecting upon what Hinges the Plot mov'd, thrusts the Queen Dowager <hi>Edward the fourth's</hi> Widow into the Nunnery of <hi>Berdmonsey,</hi> and seizes all her Lands and Goods, orders <hi>Edward Plantagenet</hi> then a close Prisoner in the Tower, to be shewn to the People in the most notorious and publick manner that could be devised; and sets forth a Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of general Pardon, to all that would reveal their Off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nces and submit by a day, all which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sults of the Councel were duly Executed.</p>
               <p>In the mean while the Rebels in <hi>Ireland</hi> were not idle, but had sent private Messengers both into <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Flanders;</hi> who in both places had wrought effects of no small Importance. For in <hi>England</hi> they won to their party the Earl of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln,</hi> a person of great wit and courage, who was induced to participate with the Action of <hi>Ireland,</hi> not upon the strength of the Proceedings there, which he looked upon but as a Bubble, and as knowing the pretended <hi>Plantagenet</hi> to be but an Idol:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:43770:31"/> But upon Letters from the Dutches of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> upon whose Succors and Foundation for the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>price there seemed to be a more solid Foundation: With which resolution he sailed secretly into <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> where he met the Lord <hi>Lovel,</hi> having left a Correspondence in <hi>England</hi> with Sir <hi>Tho. Brough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> a man of great <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Dependencies</hi> in <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cashire.</hi> Thereupon it was concluded that the two Lords Assisted with a Regiment of 2000 Almains, under the Command of <hi>Martin Swart</hi> an old expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Captain, should pass over into <hi>Ireland</hi> to the new upstart King. After these two Lords were arrived in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the party taking Courage, as seeing themselves in a Body first for a Bravery Crowned their Mushroom Prince in the Cathedral Church of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and then calling a Council, it was resolved with all speed to transport their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not long after the Rebels with their King under the leading of the Earl of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> the Lord <hi>Lovel,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Kildare</hi> and Collonel <hi>Swart</hi> landed at <hi>Foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drey</hi> in <hi>Lancashire,</hi> whither repaired to them Sir <hi>Tho. Broughton</hi> with some few Companies of <hi>English.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this the King marches as far as <hi>Coventry,</hi> and from thence sent forth some Troops of light Horsemen for discovery, and to intercept some straglers for the gaining of Intelligence.</p>
               <p>But the Rebels took their way to <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rk</hi> without spoiling the Country, or committing the least Act of Hostility, the better to put themselves into the favour of the People, and personate their King as being one that was sparing and compassionate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:43770:32"/> his Subjects. But the <hi>Snowbal</hi> did not gather as was expected; so that the Earl of <hi>Lincoln</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of his hopes of the Countries Concords to him, and seeing the business past recalling, resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to make on where the King was, and to give him battle, and thereupon marched toward <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ark,</hi> thinking to have surprized the Town: But the <hi>King</hi> being reinforced with a supply of six Thousand Men, brought him by the Earl of <hi>Shrews<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> and the Lord <hi>Strange,</hi> put himself between the Enemies Camp and <hi>Newark.</hi> The Earl no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing dismayed came forward to a little Village called <hi>Stoke,</hi> and there encamped that night upon the Brow of a Hill. The next day the King presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him Battle upon the Plain; Nor did the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Earl refuse him, but coming down, joyned Battle with him: The fight was fierce and obstinate for three hours; but at length the Victory fell to the <hi>King,</hi> to whom of right it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed. The Chieftains of the Rebels, the Earl of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> the Lord <hi>Lovel,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Kildare,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Broughton</hi> and <hi>Swart</hi> were all slain: The Young Counterfeit <hi>Plantagenet,</hi> now <hi>Lambert Simnel</hi> again with his Crafty Tutor were all taken Prisoners, so that the King was now absolute Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of the whole Rebellion. As for <hi>Lambert Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> he was preferred from wearing a Counterfeit Crown to be a turn-broach in the Kings Kitching: and his Tutor being committed a close Prisoner, was never heard of more. All the <hi>Adherents</hi> and <hi>Abettors</hi> of these <hi>Rebels</hi> were strictly enquired after, and some punished by Death, others by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43770:32"/> Fines and Ransomes, which though it spared Death, reduc'd the unwary partakers to want and pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, far worse then Death.</p>
               <p>Not long after the Parliament having given the <hi>King</hi> a considerable <hi>Subsidy,</hi> when it came to be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy'd in the Counties of <hi>Yorkshire</hi> and <hi>Durham,</hi> the People upon a suddain grew into a great Mutiny, openly Declaring, That they neither would nor could pay the <hi>Subsidy.</hi> Of this the Earl of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland</hi> wrote to the <hi>King,</hi> praying his <hi>Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> wrote peremptorily back, That he would not endure the base Multitude should fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate the <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> wherein their <hi>Votes</hi> and <hi>Consents</hi> were concluded. This message being made known did so incense the Multitude, that immediately routing together, they assail'd the Earl of <hi>Northumberland</hi> in his own <hi>House,</hi> with se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of his Servants; And then Creating for their <hi>Leader</hi> one Sir <hi>John Egremomd</hi> a Factious Person, and withal animated by a base Fellow, call'd <hi>John a Chamber,</hi> a very meer <hi>Incendiary,</hi> who therefore bare a great sway among the <hi>Imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ruous Vulgar,</hi> they brake forth into open <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and gave out in flat terms, That they would March against the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Fight</hi> with him for the maintenance of their <hi>Liberty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Against these the <hi>King</hi> sent the Earl of <hi>Surrey</hi> with a Competent Power, who fought and defeated the Rebels, and took their F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re-brand, <hi>John a Chamber,</hi> alive; whose Glorious Reward for taking Armes against his Prince was, to be Executed at <hi>York</hi> in great State: For he was <hi>Hang'd</hi> upon a Gibbet rais'd a <hi>Stage</hi> higher, in the middle of a <hi>Square Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:43770:33"/> as a <hi>Traytor Paramount;</hi> while a certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Men that were his chief <hi>Accomplices,</hi> were <hi>Hang'd</hi> up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the lower Story round about him.</p>
               <p>Upon the like Occasion, that is upon disgust ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a <hi>Subsidy</hi> that was about to be levy'd in <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall,</hi> the People of that County likewise began to Mutiny and Murmure, Crying out, <hi>That it was for them to pay that had too much, and liv'd Idly, but as for themselves, they would eat the Bread which they got with th sweat of their Brows, and no body should take it from them.</hi> Being thus in a ferment, they lighted upon two <hi>Ringlead<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs</hi> suitable to their Humour, the one a <hi>Black-smith,</hi> or <hi>Farrier</hi> of <hi>Bodmyn,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Michael Joseph,</hi> a notable talking Fellow, and no less desirous to be talk'd of. The Name of the other was <hi>Thomas Flammock,</hi> a <hi>Petty-fogger,</hi> who bare a great sway among the Rabble. These two fail'd not to fill the Ears of the People with their <hi>Rebellious Notions,</hi> so that at their <hi>Seditious Instiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> the Multitude presently Arm'd themselves with Bows and Bills, and such other Weapons as their Habitations afforded; and forthwith under the Command of their <hi>Leader,</hi> took their March out of <hi>Cornwall</hi> thorough <hi>Devon-shire</hi> to <hi>Taunton,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any slaughter or violence offer'd. From <hi>Taunton</hi> they Marched to <hi>Wells,</hi> where the Lord <hi>Audley,</hi> with whom their <hi>Leaders</hi> before had held some se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Intelligence, a Noble-man of an antient Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but unquiet and popular, and aspiring to his Ruine, came into them, and was accepted by them with great joy and gladness as their General, now proud that they were led by a Noble-man.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:43770:33"/>
               <p>The Lord <hi>Audley</hi> led them from <hi>Wells</hi> to <hi>Salisbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> thence the silly people not heeding their <hi>Leaders,</hi> would needs be Conducted into <hi>Kent,</hi> fancying that they should receive great assistance from the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of that Country; But the County was so well settled, that neither Gentleman nor Yeoman came into their aid, which so much dismayed many of the simple sort, that several deserted their <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Leaders,</hi> and in good ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> returned home: but those that were engaged stood by it, and rather grew proud, then fail'd in <hi>Hopes</hi> and <hi>Courage.</hi> Wherefore they kept on their way, and encamp'd upon <hi>Black Heath,</hi> between <hi>Greenwitch</hi> and <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ham,</hi> threatning to bid Battle to the <hi>King,</hi> and to take <hi>Lond n</hi> within his view, imagining with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves there to find no less fear, then wealth.</p>
               <p>While the <hi>Rebels</hi> were thus encamp'd upon the Hill from whence they might behold <hi>London,</hi> and the fair Valley about it, the <hi>King,</hi> having a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful force about him, the better to master all events and accidents, divided them into three Parts, of which he Commanded one Part to put themselves beyond the Hill where the Rebels lay encamp'd, and to be-set all the deserts and skirts of it, except those that lay toward <hi>London,</hi> to the end he might have the <hi>Wild Bears</hi> as it were in a <hi>Toyle.</hi> The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part he assign'd to the <hi>Lord Chamberlain,</hi> who was appointed to assail the <hi>Rebels</hi> in Front, from that side next toward the City. The third part he retain'd about himself, upon all events to restore the Fight, or Consummate the Victory, encamping himself to that purpose in St. <hi>George's Fields,</hi> and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:43770:34"/> puting his forces between the <hi>Rebels</hi> and the <hi>City.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> the 22d. of <hi>June,</hi> the <hi>Lord d' Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigny</hi> March'd toward the <hi>Rebels,</hi> and first beat some of their Troops from <hi>Deptford Bridge,</hi> where they fought manfully, and then charged their main Body with so much fury, that he had by his incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderate forwardness almost call'd into Dispute the Fortune of the Day; for Fighting in the Head of his Troops he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> taken Prisoner by the <hi>Rebels,</hi> but immediately rescu'd and deliver'd. The <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> maintain'd the Fight for a small time, and for their persons shew'd no want of Courage; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ill-arm'd and ill-led, without <hi>Horse</hi> and <hi>Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery,</hi> they were with no great difficulty cut to pieces, and put to flight: And for their three <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> as commonly the Captains of Commotions are but half-Courag'd Men, they suffered themselves to be taken.</p>
               <p>And now follow the Rewards of their <hi>Disloyalty.</hi> The Lord <hi>Audley</hi> was led from <hi>Newgate</hi> to <hi>Tower-hill,</hi> in a <hi>Paper Coat, Painted</hi> with his own Armes revers'd, and there Beheaded. <hi>Flammock</hi> and the <hi>Black-smith</hi> were <hi>Hang'd, Drawn,</hi> and <hi>Quarter'd,</hi> at <hi>Tyburn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now comes <hi>Perkin Warbeck</hi> upon the Stage, a Youth of <hi>Time, Favour,</hi> and <hi>Shape,</hi> and one that had such a crafty and bewitching manner; both to move pity, and induce belief, as was like a kind of <hi>Fascination</hi> or <hi>Inchantment</hi> to those that saw or heard him. Besides that, <hi>King Edward</hi> the Fourth had done his Father a Converted <hi>Jew</hi> the Honour to be his <hi>Godfather.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:43770:34"/>
               <p>This Youth the Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> finding for her turn kept by her a great while, with great secresie, and instructed him by many Cabinet Conferences, how to act his part. When she thought him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in his Lesson, she sent him into <hi>Ireland,</hi> where he took upon him the Person of the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and drew to himself Accomplices and Partakers by all the ways he could devise, insomuch that he wrote Letters to the Earls of <hi>Desmond</hi> and <hi>Kildare,</hi> to come to his aid.</p>
               <p>When he was in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to embrace all advantages against the King of <hi>England,</hi> and instigated by several <hi>English Fugitives</hi> then in his Court, and already prepared by the Dutchess of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> sent over to <hi>Perkin</hi> two <hi>English Renegado</hi>'s in the Nature of <hi>Embassadors,</hi> to advertise the upstart of his good Inclinations to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him, and that he was resolv'd to aid h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m to recover his Right against <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Usurper</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Enemy</hi> of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this <hi>Perkin</hi> Sail'd over into <hi>France,</hi> where the King received him with great Honour, stil'd him by the Name of the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> lodg'd and accommodated him in great State, and assign'd him a Guard for his Person. Thither also several <hi>English Male-contents</hi> of Quality repair'd to him, as Sir <hi>George Nevil,</hi> and about a Hundred more.</p>
               <p>But this being only a trick on the <hi>French King</hi>'s part to bow King <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nry</hi> to Peace; no sooner was the Treaty entred into, but <hi>Perkin</hi> was warn'd and dismiss'd out of <hi>France,</hi> from whence he again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires to the Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> into <hi>Flanders,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:43770:35"/> him as one that she had never seen in her Life before. At first she pretended to sift him whether he were the very Duke of <hi>York</hi> or no? but then seeming at last to be fatisfyed, she did him all Princely Honour, call'd him <hi>The White R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se of England,</hi> and appointed a Guard of 30 <hi>Halbuteers,</hi> to attend his Person.</p>
               <p>These Reports took hold of divers, in some up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Discontent, in some upon Ambition, in some upon Levity and Desire of Change. Nor was it long before these Rumours of Novelty had begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten others of Scandal and Murmur against the <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Government,</hi> taxing him with severe Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions upon the People, and Discountenancing his Nobility. At length all these ill-humours gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a head, settled in several eminent persons, as the Lord <hi>Stanley,</hi> the Lord <hi>Fitz Walter,</hi> Sir <hi>Simon Montford,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Thwaites,</hi> and others, though none engaged openly but Sir <hi>Robert Clifford,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Barley,</hi> who were sent into <hi>Flanders</hi> from the rest of the Conspirators, to understand the truth of Things. The Person of <hi>Clifford</hi> was extreamly welcome to the Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> and he being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the sight of <hi>Perkin,</hi> wrote over into <hi>England</hi> that he knew the Person of <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> as well as he knew his own, and that this Young-man was undoubtedly He. By which means all things grew to be prepared for Revolt and Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>England,</hi> and the Conspirators came to have Correspondeney between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King on the other side not asleep, resolves to work by Countermine, and to that purpose of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:43770:35"/> the four Persons employed by <hi>Richard</hi> in the Murder of his <hi>Nephews,</hi> causes the Examinations of two that were still alive to be taken a new and Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who attested the Murder to be absolutely done as is recited in Story. Then he employed several of his Friends to insinuate themselves into the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity of the Party in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and so to learn what Associates and Correspondents they had in <hi>England,</hi> and how far every one was engag'd; but above all if they could, to regain Sir <hi>Robert Clifford</hi> to his side, who knew the most inward of their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets.</p>
               <p>These <hi>Espialls</hi> ply'd their Charge so roundly, that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> was won to be assur'd of the King, and to be industrious and officious in his Service, so that the King was well inform'd of all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Correspondents in <hi>England;</hi> insomuch, that upon <hi>Clifford</hi>'s Discovery, the Lord <hi>Fitz Water,</hi> the Lord <hi>Hastings,</hi> Sir <hi>Simon Montfort, Ratcliff</hi> and <hi>Dawbeney</hi> were all Arra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gn'd, Condemn'd, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed. And this was the first act of <hi>Warbecks Rebellious Tragedy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However <hi>Perkin</hi> encouraged to proceed, resolv'd to try his Fortune in some attempt upon <hi>England,</hi> and to that purpose having got together a consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able force of all sorts of Nations, Bankrupts, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, and such others as liv'd by spoil and rapine, puts to Sea, and shews himself upon the Coast of <hi>Kent,</hi> about <hi>Sandwich</hi> and <hi>Deal,</hi> where some few of his People Landed; but not being followed by any <hi>English</hi> of Account, but by a sort of <hi>Free-booters,</hi> fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to spoil and ransack, then recover a Kingdom.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:43770:36"/> No body stirr'd in his behalf, only some forces were directed to shew themselves upon the Coast, and by Signs to entice <hi>Perkin</hi>'s Souldiers to Land, as if they would joyn with him; but <hi>Perkin</hi> not liking their Countenances would not stir a foot. Thereupon they fell upon those that were Landed already, and took of them about a hundred and fifty Prisoners, who for their welcome into <hi>England,</hi> were every one Hang'd, being first brought to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> rail'd in Ropes together like <hi>H rses</hi> in a <hi>Team.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this <hi>Perkin</hi> Sails into <hi>Ireland,</hi> but finding there nothing but the blustering affection of a wild and naked People, his Council advis'd him to seek aid of the King of <hi>Scotland;</hi> By him he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd in State in his Chamber of <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sence,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd in all things as became the Person of the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and was by him allow'd to Marry his near Kins-woman, a Young Virgin of excellent Beauty ond Vertue. And so far did the King of <hi>Scots</hi> espouse his Quarrel, that he enter'd <hi>England</hi> with an Army: but seeing none came in to <hi>Perkin,</hi> nor that any stirr'd in any other parts in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, he only wasted <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and return'd laden with Booty.</p>
               <p>So that at length, though he was in his own Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion perswaded that he was a Counterfeit, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in regard he had taken him into his protection, he dismiss'd him Honourably with shiping, and means, to Transport himself where he thought most for his advantage; so that he return'd a third time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>While he was there the <hi>Cornishmen,</hi> though so
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43770:36"/> lately and so generously Pardon'd by their justly incensed Prince, being returned home, were still in a heat, and not having yet laid dovvn their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal <hi>Animosities,</hi> but hatching nevv Rebellions, thought <hi>Perkin</hi> a fit Person to head their Traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Attempts,</hi> and to that purpose found meanes to send to him, to let him knovv that if he would come over to them, they would serve Him.</p>
               <p>Thereupon his Chief Councellors <hi>Hern</hi> a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, <hi>Skelton</hi> a Taylor, and <hi>Astley</hi> a Scrivener, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise him to take opportunity by the Forelock; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which incitement, with about six score fighting Men, he put to Sea, Lands at <hi>Whitston Bay,</hi> and marcht directly to <hi>Bodmin,</hi> where there assembled to him, to the number of 3000 of the ruder sort of People. There he set forth a new Declaration stroaking the people with fair promises, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouring them with invectives against the King and his Government, and then took upon himself the Title of <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chard the fourth King of England.</hi> After which he marched forward and besieged the City of <hi>Exeter;</hi> upon which he made a fierce Assault, but was driven from the Walls with great loss.</p>
               <p>Thereupon hearing of great Forces that were coming against him, he raised his siege, being at that time <hi>seven Thousand</hi> strong, and encouraged with the Oaths and Vows of the <hi>Rebels</hi> not to leave Him, till the uttermost drop of their Blood was spilt: When he was come near <hi>Taunton,</hi> the new King dissembling his fears seemed all the day to prepare for a Fight; but in the still Midnight, with about <hi>threescore Horse</hi> he fled to <hi>Bewley</hi> in the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:43770:37"/>
                  <hi>New Forrest,</hi> where he and his followers Register'd themselves for Sanctuary Men, leaving his <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> Assistants to shift or combate for themselves; who being destitute of their Head, without a stroke strucken, submitted all to the Kings Mercy, who were all a second time pardoned by the <hi>King,</hi> except some of the most desperate and notorious Persons, whom the <hi>King</hi> reserved for the stroke of Justice. <hi>Perkin</hi> being taken out of Sanctuary, was shewed for a publick Maygame through the City, and then committed to custody; after which, having deceived his Keepers, he made his escape to the Sea Coast; but being brought back again, was set fettered in the Stocks for whole days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon a Scaffold, in the <hi>Palace Yard</hi> at <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster, Ch apside</hi> and other <hi>Places,</hi> and then laid up in the Tower, from whence, for endeavouring to procure his own, and the escape of <hi>George Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taget,</hi> by murdering the Lieutenant of the Tower, he was at length tryed by a Commission of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> and hanged at <hi>Tyburn.</hi> And this was the end of this Cockatrice of a King, whose continual slurs of Fortune plainly shewed the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Real and Counterfeit Majesty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>HENRY</hi> VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry the Eight,</hi> after the Dissolution of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys, having made some slender Reformations, and particularly given way, that the <hi>Creed,</hi> the <hi>ten Commandments,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> might be read in <hi>English,</hi> which was also Enacted by <hi>Parliament,</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:43770:37"/> the Commons discontented that their Mumblings must down, and the Monks sore troubled to min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle English in their <hi>Masses,</hi> the <hi>Lincolnsh re</hi> men began a Commotion under Duke <hi>Mackarel,</hi> a <hi>Monk</hi> who named himself <hi>Captain Cobler,</hi> and his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers were sweld near to the number of <hi>twenty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand.</hi> Against these the King prepared in Person, sending forth into several Counties, to charge them with a Levy of so many well appointed Souldiers to meet him at <hi>Ampthil;</hi> which being known to the Rebels, they were so bold as to send to the <hi>King</hi> several <hi>Articles</hi> subscribed with many of their Hands, demanding the Restitution of <hi>Abbeys,</hi> the removal of <hi>Cromwel</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Rich,</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of the Augmentations, and several of the Bishops. But these Rebels seeing the Kings For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces grow upon 'em, were soon dissipated by the meer Breach of a General Pardon, so that they submitted themselves to the Kings Mercy, after a vain Breath of their Allegiance.</p>
               <p>Yet did not their ill success daunt the Northern Commoners, who threatned a severer Storm: For in <hi>Yorkshire</hi> there Assembled no less then <hi>forty Thousand</hi> Rusticks well furnished with <hi>Horse, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, Artilery</hi> and other <hi>War-like Habiliments,</hi> threatning to set the stay of the State upon their Giddy Inventions; their pretence was Religion and the Defence of the Holy Church. Their <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> Painted with the four Wounds of Christ, the <hi>Challice</hi> and the <hi>Cakes,</hi> and upon their <hi>Sleevs</hi> was writ the Name of the Lord; and so fervent were they in their Proceedings, that this attempt of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:43770:38"/> theirs must be called the <hi>Holy Pilgrimage:</hi> Nor were the <hi>Boores</hi> and <hi>Swains</hi> only involved in this Insurrection, but others of Place and Degree, as the Archbishop of <hi>York,</hi> the Lord <hi>Darcy,</hi> the Lord <hi>Lumley,</hi> with several Knights and Bayliffs of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations,</hi> but their Captain General was one <hi>Robert Aske</hi> a mean Gentleman, to whom one <hi>Rudstone</hi> was Associate in the Field: Other Commanders they had out of the Common Rabble, of whom the Chief was one <hi>James Diamond</hi> General of the Foot, a poor Fisherman who styl'd himself the Earl of <hi>Poverty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These set forth a Declaration, subscribed to all <hi>Lords, Knights, Masters</hi> and <hi>Friends,</hi> wherein they declared their Intentions to Fight against all that should oppose them in their Pilgrimage for the Punishment of <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Lawyers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And so terrible and haughty was their <hi>Captain Ask,</hi> that when <hi>Lancaster Herald</hi> was sent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the <hi>Kings Message</hi> to them at <hi>Pomfrait Castle,</hi> which the <hi>Rebels</hi> had got by surrender from the Lord <hi>Darcy,</hi> he so blustered out his Answers, that the poor spirited Fellow excusing himself to be but a <hi>Messenger,</hi> fell before him on his Knees: These Rebels also sent forth their Mandates for the Country to come into their Assistance, under penalty of pulling down their Houses, loosing their Goods, and their Persons to be at the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains disposal.</p>
               <p>Against these the King sent the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> accompanied with Marquis of <hi>Exeter,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Huntington</hi> and <hi>Rutland,</hi> who joyning their
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:43770:38"/> Forces together, made toward the Rebels then ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near <hi>Doncaster,</hi> in whose sight they immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately set up their <hi>Tents,</hi> resolving the next day to give them Battle. But in the Night time such Floods of Water fell, that the River <hi>Don</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed its Banks, so that there was no passage over the Bridge, Thereupon the Lord General offered the Rebels a Parley, which being with much ado accepted, at length this Meteor of an Infurrection was also Disolved by the warm Rayes of the <hi>Kings</hi> Pardon, and the Multitude melted away like Hail in Spring; but Heaven determining to bring these boisterous Rebels to a more remarkable Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, neither could this gentleness of the King reclaim their tumultuous Rage, so that after they had taken a little breath, a new Insurrection was set on Foot in the same Places, and by the same <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, Dacres, Ash,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Constable,</hi> Sir <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Bigot, Dulmer, Peircy, Tempest, Hamilton</hi> and <hi>Lumley,</hi> who being taken in this last attempt, were all put to Death, as well they deserved. In which Executions they were accompanyed by four <hi>Abbots,</hi> three <hi>Monks,</hi> two <hi>Priors,</hi> one <hi>Parson</hi> and five <hi>Priests,</hi> together with Captain <hi>Cobler</hi> their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, who were all hanged at the same time for Treason.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>EDWARD</hi> VI.</head>
               <p>In this Young Princes <hi>Raign</hi> the Commons grew very mutinous, some murmuring at the Inclosing of Lands, some at the change of Religion, so that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:43770:39"/> they rose almost at one and the same time, in <hi>Oxfordshire, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vonshire, Norfolk</hi> and <hi>Yorkshire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Those in <hi>Oxfordshire</hi> were soon dissipated by a force of <hi>one Thousand five Hundred</hi> Men led against them by the Lord <hi>Grey,</hi> and their Chief Leaders taken and hanged by Martial Law.</p>
               <p>But in <hi>Devonshire</hi> the Insurrection grew to be better formed, set on by many of the old dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded Priests, who ran in among them. They grew in a short time to be <hi>ten Thousand</hi> strong, a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainst whom the Lord <hi>Russel</hi> was sent with a small force to stop their Proceedings; Who remembring how the Duke of <hi>Norsolk</hi> had broken a formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Rebellion in the North, with a small Army, kept at a distance, hoping that time would Weaken and Disunite these <hi>Rebels;</hi> but his delays gave them Advantage and Strength. who were now led by some Gentlemen, of whom <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Cornwal</hi> was Chief.</p>
               <p>Thereupon they sent to the King for the redress of their Greivances; in Answer to which the King required their Obedience and Submission to his Royal Authority, as others had done; to whom for so doing he had already not only shewed Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but granted redress of their just grievances, otherwise that they were to expect the utmost se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity that Traytors deserved.</p>
               <p>But nothing prevailed upon this inraged Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, whom the Priests inflamed withal the Artifice Imaginable.</p>
               <p>In this heat they marched forward and beseiged <hi>Exeter,</hi> where the Citizens resisted them with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:43770:39"/> great Courage and Resolution; so that the Rebels finding they could do nothing by force, resolved to lie about the Town, and starve it to a surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>At first the Lord <hi>Russel</hi> finding himself too weak, retired to <hi>Hamilton,</hi> but perceiving they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a Bridge behind him, he was forced to an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, wherein he slew <hi>six Hundred</hi> of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels without any loss, By which he understood their Courages were Mortal, and that they could not stand a brisk Charge, nor rally again when disordered, so that having received a recuite of Men, he return'd to raise the seige of <hi>Exeter,</hi> where the Citizens were by that time reduced to eat their Horses; but they resolved to suffer any great extremity, rather then to fall into the hands of these Savages: while they lay before the Town, the Rebels had blocked up all the ways, and had left <hi>two Thousand</hi> men to keep a Bridge which the Kings forces were to pass; but the Lord <hi>Russel</hi> brake through 'em, and killed above a Thousand upon the place; upon which the <hi>Rebels</hi> rais'd their siege, and retired with ignominie to <hi>Lanceston.</hi> The Lord <hi>Russel</hi> pursu'd the Fugitives in their Conster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, who now beginning to draw off in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, were killed in great numbers. The Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders themselves were also taken. For it is the Overruling appointment of Providence, that Traytors and Rebels generally choose rather to fall into the Hands of Exemplary Justice, then to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice their pusillanimous Souls, to the Honour of their vile cause. And therefore <hi>Arund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi> the May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:43770:40"/> of <hi>Bodmin</hi> and two of their Arch Priests, with seven more of the most Illustrious of the Crew, were splendidly Hanged to attone for the rest of the deluded Multitude.</p>
               <p>But the Rebels in <hi>Norfolk</hi> stood it out somewhat more boldly, being led by one <hi>Ket</hi> a Tanner. They pretended nothing of Religion but to suppress and destroy the Gentry, and to put new Counsellors about the King. These increased to the number of <hi>twenty Thousand,</hi> and committing many Outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: The Sheriff of the County came boldly to them and required them to disperse, but had he not been well mounted, he had paid for his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing.</p>
               <p>Against these the Marquiss of <hi>Northampton</hi> was sent with <hi>one Thousand one Hundred</hi> Men, who marched into <hi>Norwich,</hi> where the Rebels were not a little Elevated in their Thoughts, so that their Captain <hi>Kett</hi> erected a Tribunal under an Oak, which was called the Oak of Reformation: where the haughty Tanner sate in Judgment upon all whom they thought fit to call offenders.</p>
               <p>The Marquisses ill success being understood at Court, the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> was sent away with <hi>six Thousand</hi> foot and <hi>one Thousand five Hundred Horse;</hi> who coming to <hi>Norwich,</hi> was however scarce able to defend the Town, for the Rebels fell often in upon him, besides that he was not well assured of the City it self. At length he so laid his forces as to cut off all Provision from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, who thereupon having wasted all the <hi>Country</hi> round about 'em, were forc'd to remove: Then the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:43770:40"/> Earl followed 'em close with his Horse, and tho the Rebels turned upon him, and made a stout re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance for a time, yet he quickly routed the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Croud, of whom he slew <hi>two Thousand</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the place, and then took their famous Captain <hi>Ket</hi> Prisoner, together with his Brother and seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others, of which nine were hanged upon <hi>Ket's Oak</hi> of <hi>Reformation,</hi> which never till then bare fruit so proper to the Nature of its Name. <hi>Ket's</hi> Brother was hanged upon the Steeple of <hi>Wymond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and the Arch-Rebel himself was hanged in Chains upon the Castle of <hi>Norwich,</hi> whose Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens annually solemnized the day of their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with no less joy then the <hi>Jews</hi> did when they had escaped the <hi>Hands</hi> of wicked <hi>Haman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These <hi>Hazards</hi> thus appeased in the West and East, the North would likewise come in for a Cast, under the leading of one <hi>Ombler</hi> a Yeoman, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Dale</hi> a Parish Clark, and one <hi>Stevenson</hi> the Post; their pretences were to disburden the Land of all Grievances.</p>
               <p>Their number was now encreased to <hi>three Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand,</hi> so that the better sort began to grow in great fear of their Lives and Estates. But presently down came the News of the defeat in other parts, which being followed by the Kings pardon with proffers of Life, <hi>Ombler</hi> and <hi>Dale</hi> were quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken, and almost left alone, and so being easily ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, they two, with four more of the principal Ring-leaders were hanged at <hi>York,</hi> according to their deserts, for publick Examples, as being the best Books for the unruly Vulgar to read in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:43770:41"/>
               <head>Queen <hi>MARY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>After the Death of <hi>Edward the Sixth,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Northumberland</hi> made a heavy bustle to advance the Lady <hi>Jane Gray</hi> to the throne of <hi>England.</hi> But such was the prevalency of Legal Right, over the ill grounded Claims of usurpation, that no sooner did <hi>Mary</hi> appear in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> in the challenge of her Inheritance, but while the Title of <hi>Jane</hi> was Proclaiming in the <hi>Towns</hi> near <hi>London,</hi> the People were all flocking to the Lawful <hi>Heiress;</hi> so that the Duke, who was sent to reduce his Lawful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigness to pretended obedience, finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self forsaken by the Council, who were seasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly sensible of their Error, and seeing that no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy came into his Assistance, as pusillanimously as he had Traiterously engaged in an ill design, deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himself, dismissed his forces, and going to the Market place in <hi>Cambridg,</hi> was one of the first that proclaimed the Lawful Queen; by whom the Earl of <hi>Arundel</hi> being sent to apprehend him, in a most abject manner he fell at the Earles Feet to beg his favour; but all nothing availed him, for he was sent to the <hi>Tower</hi> with three of his Sons; and soon after Beheaded with Sir <hi>John Gates</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Palmer,</hi> tvvo of his great <hi>Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next thing that gave Offence was, the March with <hi>Spain,</hi> which had Influence of many; but the chief Conspirators were, the Duke of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> Sir <hi>Peter Carew,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Wyat;</hi> the one was to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:43770:41"/> raise the <hi>Midland Counties,</hi> the other <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and <hi>Wyat Kent.</hi> But as <hi>Carew</hi> was carrying on his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign in the <hi>West,</hi> the Conspiracy happened to be discovered by one that he had intrusted too far: and thereupon <hi>Carew</hi> fled into <hi>France.</hi> The Duke always a Person of a mean Spirit, after a faint en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to act his part, gave it over, and conceal'd himself in a private House, where he was betrayed to the Earl of <hi>Huntington,</hi> by him to whom he had intrusted himself, and carryed to the <hi>Tower.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wyat</hi> searing to be undone by the Discovery al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made, gathered some Men together and Marched to <hi>Maidstone,</hi> where he made Proclaima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>That he intended nothing but to prese<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve the Liberty of the Nation, and keep it from coming under the Yoke of Strangers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Against him the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> was sent with 600 <hi>Foot,</hi> and 200 <hi>Horse,</hi> Commanded by one <hi>Bret.</hi> But the <hi>Londoners</hi> being wrought upon by one <hi>Harp,</hi> that <hi>Wyat</hi> intended nothing but the preservation of the Nation from the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and a deep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuation that none would suffer under that Yoke more then they went over with their Captains to <hi>Wyat,</hi> so that the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> was forc'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat. <hi>Wyats</hi> Party thus encreasing they turn'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>London,</hi> and at <hi>Deptford</hi> were met by two of the <hi>Privy-Council,</hi> who were sent <hi>in the Queens Name,</hi> to demand what would content them? In answer to which <hi>Wyat</hi> demanded the <hi>Command</hi> of the <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and that the Queen might be under his Guard.</p>
               <p>Upon these extravagant Propositions, the <hi>Privy-Counsellors</hi> return, and <hi>Wyat</hi> enters <hi>Southwark</hi> four
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:43770:42"/> thousand strong, in hopes the City would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for him; but finding the Bridge shut against him, he cross'd the River at <hi>Kingston,</hi> and thence Marching directly for <hi>London,</hi> advanc'd as far as <hi>Charing-Cross.</hi> There the Lord <hi>Clinton</hi> fell in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the several Bodies of his Men, and dispersed them so, that he had scarce five hundred left about him; but with those that remain'd, he passed through the <hi>Strand</hi> and <hi>Fleet-street</hi> up to <hi>Ludgate,</hi> in hopes to have found the Gates open to him; but those hopes being frustrated, he return'd back, and being now out of all heart, was taken at <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-Bar</hi> by a <hi>Herald.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Soon after the Duke of <hi>Suffolk</hi> was Condemn'd by his Peers, and Beheaded. <hi>Wyat</hi> being brought to his Tryal, begg'd his Life in a most pitiful and abject manner, but for all that his Head was se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd from his Shoulders. <hi>Bret</hi> was Hang'd in Chains at <hi>Rochester:</hi> in all fifty eight were Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in several places, and six hundred of the Rabble were order'd to come before the Queen with <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> about their Necks to beg their Lives.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Queen <hi>ELIZABETH.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The first that desturb'd the quiet of this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, were the two Earls of <hi>Northumberland</hi> and <hi>Westmorland,</hi> both <hi>Zealous Catholicks;</hi> who could not carry their Conspiracy so closely, but that the Rumour of their frequent meetings encreased in such sort, that the Queen, by peremptory Letters Commanded them (all excuses set apart) to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:43770:42"/> before her, to the end she might quite deter them from <hi>Rebellion,</hi> or else that they might be forced to break out forthwith, before they could gather their forces together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Northumberland</hi> being a Person of an easie Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Conscious of his own Guilt, waver'd in a careful doubt whither he should go to the Queen, or flie, or break out into open <hi>Hostility.</hi> His Friends and Servants already prepared for the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,</hi> seeing him thus wavering and fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul, to awaken his drowsie humour, came to him in the Dead of the Night, crying out, <hi>That his Enemies were at hand to carry him away Prisoner,</hi> beseeching him withal, not to neglect himself, his friends, nor the Religion of his Fathers: who thereupon in a trembling condition with-drew himself to a <hi>House</hi> of the Earl of <hi>Westmorlands,</hi> where several who were not ignorant of the Matter were already assembled.</p>
               <p>Their pretences were several; to some they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the defence of the <hi>Queen:</hi> to others the restauration of the <hi>Catholick Religion:</hi> and to others that they were forced to take Armes, least the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Nobility of <hi>England</hi> should be troden under foot by new Upstarts. Upon these Grounds they rush into open <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and set forth a Writing, <hi>That they had not taken Armes with any other intent, but that the</hi> Religion <hi>of their fore-Fathers might be restored, Corrupt Counsells remov'd from the Queen, and the Duke, and other faithful Lords restored to their</hi> Rank <hi>and</hi> Dignity, <hi>to</hi> Liberty <hi>and</hi> Grace. They al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so sent Letters to the <hi>Papists</hi> throughout the whole
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:43770:43"/> Kingdom, to joyn their forces with theirs: but they were so far from Associating themselves, that most of them sent the Letters which they receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed togethet with the Bearers, to the Queen.</p>
               <p>The Rebels went first to <hi>Durham,</hi> where they rent and trampled under foot the <hi>English Bibles,</hi> and Books of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> which they foun'd in the <hi>Churches.</hi> From thence they Marched easie Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches under their Colours, wherein were painted in some the five wounds of <hi>Christ,</hi> in others a <hi>Chalice,</hi> as far as <hi>Clifford Moore,</hi> where they mustered their Army to the number of 4000 <hi>Foot,</hi> and 600 <hi>Horse.</hi> Here when they understood that forces were eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where rais'd against them, and that <hi>Carlisle</hi> was reinforc'd with fresh supplies, they retreated the same way they went, and coming to <hi>Bernard</hi>'s Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, they took it for want of Victuals by Composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Upon which very day, they being now Proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Traytors to their Country, the Earl of <hi>Sussex</hi> Marched against them with 7000 Men, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the Earl of <hi>Rutland,</hi> the Lords <hi>Hunsdon, Ferrers,</hi> and <hi>Willoughby</hi> of <hi>Parham.</hi> When <hi>Sussex</hi> was arriv'd at <hi>Aukland,</hi> the Rebels in a most fearful Consternation fled to <hi>Hexam,</hi> and shortly after in scatter'd Parties, came through by-ways to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> Castle, where understanding that the Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> and <hi>Clinton</hi> Lord Admiral pursued them with a power of 12000 Men, the two Rebellious Earls presently withdrew themselves into <hi>Scotland: Westmorland</hi> lurkt privily at <hi>Harclaw</hi> in poor Cottages among the <hi>Grahams,</hi> Famous Thieves,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:43770:43"/> by whom he was delivered into <hi>Murray</hi>'s hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Northumberland</hi> found a sculking place with <hi>Car, Furmhurst,</hi> and <hi>Bucklugh,</hi> at length escaped with some <hi>English-men</hi> into the <hi>Neitherlands,</hi> where he led a very poor Life, even to his old Age, living upon a sorry Pension from the <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Threescore Petty Constables and others were Hang'd for a Terror at <hi>Durham,</hi> among whom the Man of most note one <hi>Plumtree,</hi> a <hi>Priest.</hi> At <hi>York</hi> were Executed four more, and at <hi>London</hi> two more, and some others else-where.</p>
               <p>Afterwards such of the Rebels as were of best note were Convicted of <hi>High-Treason,</hi> and proscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. The Earl of <hi>Westmorland</hi> and <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> The Countess of <hi>Northumberland: Edward Dacres</hi> of <hi>Morton: John Nevil</hi> of <hi>Leversedge: John Swineborn: Thomas Marhenfield: Egremond Ratcliff:</hi> The Earl of <hi>Sussex</hi>'s Brother: Four of the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons:</hi> and two <hi>Tempests:</hi> with about fifty more of Noble Birth. Such bitter Fruits did the <hi>Tree of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> bare.</p>
               <p>Out of the smother'd Fire of this <hi>Rebellion,</hi> broke forth a new flame at <hi>Naworth,</hi> kindled by <hi>Leonard Dacres,</hi> second Son of <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Dacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> of <hi>Gillesland,</hi> who having got together 3000 of the rank Rioters of the Borders, and some others ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the Family of the <hi>Dacres,</hi> then in great Repute in the <hi>North,</hi> fortifyed the Castle of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> and stood at <hi>defiance</hi> against his <hi>lawful Princess.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Against these Marched the Lord <hi>Hunsdon,</hi> with the old Garrison Souldiers of <hi>Barwick.</hi> The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels not trusting to their strong Holds, Marched
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:43770:44"/> forth to encounter him; the Fight was maintained on both sides very sharply, while <hi>Leonard</hi> omitted nothing that could be expected from a Valiant Leader. But after the loss of many of his Men he left the Victory to the Lord <hi>Hunsdon,</hi> and fled into <hi>Scotland;</hi> from whence he crossed the Seas into the <hi>Neitherlands,</hi> and Dyed a poor Man at <hi>Lovaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometime after a Rebellion was hatching in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk;</hi> For certain Gentlemen of the County having an intention to set the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> at Liberty, had laid a Plot, that when the People resorted to a Fair at <hi>Harleston,</hi> they would gather the Multitude together by the sound of a Trumpet, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of repelling the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> out of <hi>England,</hi> who had withdrawn themselves in great numbers into those parts, for fear of the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi>'s Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny. Of these Gentlemen, several were brought to their Tryals, and Condemn'd of <hi>High-Treason,</hi> but three only Executed, among whom was <hi>John Throckmorton,</hi> of chiefest note, who at the Bar stood mute, but at the Gallows confessed himself the principal Author and Perswader of the Rebellion intended.</p>
               <p>No less fatal were the Rebellions in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the Authors and Contrivers of them. <hi>Shan O Neale</hi> driven to that distress, that he was once minded to have submitted himself with a <hi>Halter</hi> about his Neck to the Lord Deputy: afterwards slain by his own Relations and Country-men, in revenge of a Rape committed upon the Wife of <hi>O Donnel.</hi> The great Earl of <hi>Desmond</hi> slain in a little Cottage, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had escaped the hands of the <hi>Victorious Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:43770:44"/> for almost two years together, lurking up and down in private Holes and Corners. <hi>Hugh Roe Mac Makon,</hi> a potent Lord in the Territory of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naghan,</hi> subjected to a Tryal by Common Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and by their Sentences Hang'd, and his large Possessions divided among the <hi>English. Tea Mac Hugh</hi> taken, and his Head sent to <hi>Doublin.</hi> And lastly the haughty <hi>Tyr-Owen</hi> brought to prostrate himself before the Lord Deputy, and in the sordid Weeds of an abject Suppilant to implore the Queens Mercy. Traytors thus at length betray themselves to be the vilest and most degenerate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons living, whose Souls can endure the Torments of such low and sordid Condescentions as these? For who would not scorn to exchange his Liberty for a Pardon? or to Rebel with a Design to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase the Prolongation of an Ignominious Life, at the expence of a slavish Prostration at his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphers feet? or to be beholding to a defy'd Enemy for a Precarious Being?</p>
               <p>Nor must we omit that in the Reign of this Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous Princess, when the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> was order'd to second the <hi>Spanish Invasion of England,</hi> he had no less then 700 <hi>English Fugitives, Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traytors</hi> to their Princess in his Army; Of whom it is said, That of all others they were the least esteemed: and that neither <hi>Stanley</hi> who had the <hi>Command</hi> of them, nor <hi>Westmorland,</hi> nor others who both offered their Service and Council, were once heard: but for their unnaturalness to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Country they were debar'd of all Access, as most inauspici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous persons, worthily, and with <hi>detestation</hi> rejected.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:43770:45"/>
               <head>King <hi>JAMES.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Upon the Death of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the <hi>Popish Priests</hi> and their <hi>Bigotted Party</hi> began to conceive fresh hopes of bringing about their Designs of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advancing the <hi>Papal Interest</hi> in the Nation; but finding themselves defeated by the coming in and quiet Reception of King <hi>James,</hi> they contriv'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether a most desperate peice of Treachery, to sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize the Persons of the King and Prince, <hi>Henry</hi> his Son. Nor did they make any doubt of forces to effect it, meaning to retain them Prisoners in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and with the treasure there to maintain the Enterprize. Or if the <hi>Tower</hi> were not to be taken, then to carry their <hi>Royal Pledges</hi> to <hi>Dover Castle,</hi> and there by violence to obtain their own Pardons, a Toleration in Religion, and a Removal of Counsellors of State, not fitting for their purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</p>
               <p>To conceal this Treason, <hi>Watson</hi> the Priest devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses Oaths of Secresie; he himself, together with one <hi>Clark</hi> a Priest, instilling into the heads of the Confederators, That the King was no King before his Coronation.</p>
               <p>Persons of note in this Conspiracy were, the Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi> Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Witton,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> Sir <hi>Graftham Markham,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, George Brook, Bartholomew Brooksby,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Copley.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this Conspiracy being seasonably discover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they were every one Apprehended, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:43770:45"/> to several Prisons in <hi>London;</hi> from whence being carryed to <hi>Winchester,</hi> they were Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of <hi>High-Treason,</hi> and Sentenc'd to Dye. <hi>Watson</hi> and <hi>Clark</hi> the two Priests, and <hi>George Brooker,</hi> were all three Executed, as being Plotters and Enticers of their Associates. The Lords, with the rest that were Condemned, were Repriev'd upon the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, to render the Kings mercy the more unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, the more highly to be valu'd by the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHARLES</hi> the First.</head>
               <p>We are now coming to the Toping Rebellion of the World, the most insane, and yet the most una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Hudle and Chaos of Destraction that ever appear'd since the Creation, and yet so finely and so dexterously cemented by the cunning <hi>Architects</hi> of the Confusion of those Times, that they foild an Unfortunate Prince in the Field, though in his Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine they at length wrought their own Destruction, as by the sequel will appear.</p>
               <p>Among the chief pretences, that gave Birth and Encouragement to this Unnatural Rebellion, the most remarkable that led the Van, were those that lye always ready to be improv'd by the subtil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers of National Confusion, Religion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd ill management of Publick Affairs; And these were heightned at such a <hi>Conjuncture</hi> of <hi>Time,</hi> when the people grown wanton with luxurious plenty, and a long Peace, were fitted to admit the pleasing alterations of Tumult and Disorder. And
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:43770:46"/> yet such was the fatal Blindness of these Unruly People, that they suffered themselves to be sway'd, and to have those very Grievances, and ten times worse by their own Ambitious <hi>Tyrants,</hi> for Redress whereof, they had taken illegal Arms against their lawful Sovereign.</p>
               <p>But the chiefest Corruption of the People pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from their Seducers, of whom the chiefest part were such as fairly pretended to be the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of Christ, and Gods Embassadors, who layed claim to a Rite to Govern every one his Parish, and their Assembly the whole Nation. These per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons made it their business to decry the Rites and Ceremonies then us'd and practis'd in the Church, which begat several Invectives against the Bishops and their Ecclesiastical Government. So strange it was and yet so true, That the miseries and distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which ensu'd, should be deriv'd from no greater beginnings then only a few Ceremon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, and that a War, which never stands upon any, should be grounded and fix'd upon them.</p>
               <p>Others there were of the better sort, who having been so Educated, as to have read in their Youth the Writings of several Famous Men, concerning the <hi>Grecian</hi> and <hi>Roman Commonwealths,</hi> wherein <hi>Popular Government</hi> was extoll'd by the Glorious Name of <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Monarchy</hi> disgrac'd by the Name of <hi>Tyranny,</hi> they became in love with that Form of Government; out of which were chosen the Greatest, or the most Eloquent of the <hi>House of Commons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The City, and other great Towns of <hi>Trade,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:43770:46"/> the Prosperity of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> after their Revolt from the King of <hi>Spa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> and were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to think the like Prosperity would happen to them from the like change of Government.</p>
               <p>Others there were, and those in a very great number, who had either wasted their Fortunes, or thought them too mean for the great parts of which they believed themselves to be Masters, while others that had able Bodies, saw no better way to get their Bread, then by Fishing in troubl'd Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. All these long'd for War, hoping to live more splendidly by the lucky choice of a Party to side with, and therefore generally serv'd them who had most plenty of Money.</p>
               <p>But lastly, the people were in general so igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of their Duties, that not one perhaps of a thousand, knew what right any Man had to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him, or what necessity there was of a King, for whom he was to part with his Money against his will; So that the People being thus Principl'd of themselves, were easily made the Kings Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies by the Indefatigable Preaching of the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Ministers,</hi> and the <hi>Seditious Whisperings</hi> of False and Ignorant Politicians.</p>
               <p>At this Unfortunate Time a Parliament was call'd, to sit at <hi>Westminster</hi> the 3d. of <hi>Novemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> 1640. to determin the Differences to them, by Agreement, refer'd between the King and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now the <hi>Mutinous Democraticks</hi> being got together, first they call'd in Question such as had either Preach'd or Written in Defence of those
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:43770:47"/> Rites that belong'd to the Crown; And for those that had been Imprison'd for Writing and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermons and Books tending to <hi>Sedition,</hi> by their own <hi>Authority</hi> they order'd their setting at Liberty. In the next place they accus'd the King of a Purpose to Introduce and Authorize the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Religion,</hi> than which nothing was more hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the People; and to deprive the King of such Ministers, as by their Courage, Wisdom, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, they thought most able to prevent or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose their Designs against the King; They first Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach'd the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> of <hi>High-Treason,</hi> who was soon after Beheaded. Afterwards they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and got him lay'd up fast in the <hi>Tower:</hi> And to make sure of their sitting, they obtain'd of the King to pass an Act, That the present Parliament should continue, till both Houses should consent to the Dissolution of it.</p>
               <p>Their next Dispute was, concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> which, because the King would not part withal, as being the undoubted Right of his <hi>Prerogative Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> they told him plainly, That they should be forc'd, unless he would consent to their desires, to dispose of the <hi>Militia</hi> by the Authority of both Houses, for the safety of His Majesty, and the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>To which purpose they resolved in case of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream danger, and of His Majesties refusal, the Ordinance agreed upon by both Houses for the <hi>Militia,</hi> did oblige the People by the Fundamental Laws of the People; to back which, they added
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:43770:47"/> farther, that when the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, which is the <hi>Supreme Court</hi> of <hi>Judicature</hi> in the Kingdom, shall declare what the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> is, to have that not only questioned but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted, was a high breach of the <hi>Priviledge</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> which was not only to take the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> but the <hi>Legislative Power</hi> also from the King, who as he only made the <hi>Laws,</hi> had only <hi>Power</hi> to declare what the <hi>Law</hi> was.</p>
               <p>Much about this time the <hi>King</hi> being retir'd to <hi>York</hi> from the affronts and clamours of the Insolent and Audacious City Tumults, the <hi>Democraticks</hi> sent down Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> to secure that Town and <hi>Magazine</hi> for their use; so that when the King came to demand with only some of his own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestick Servants and some few of the Gentlemen of the County, he was denyed, entrance by the said Sir <hi>John</hi> then standing upon the Wall: For which, when the King required Justice to be done him, and that the <hi>Town</hi> and <hi>Magazine</hi> might be delivered into his Hands, the <hi>Democraticks</hi> return'd no answer, but in a Declaration full of slanders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his Majesties Government published.</p>
               <p>That whatsoever they declared to be Law, was not to be questioned.</p>
               <p>That no Precedents could be limits to bound their Proceedings.</p>
               <p>That the Parliament for the publick good might dispose of any thing wherein the King or People had right.</p>
               <p>That the Soveraign Power resided in the Houses, and that the King was to have no Negative Voice.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:43770:48"/>
               <p>That the Levying of Forces against the perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal commands of the King is not Levying War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the King, but Levying War against his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick Person, his <hi>Laws,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Treason</hi> could not be committed against the King otherwise then as he is entrusted with the Kingdom and discharges his <hi>Trust,</hi> and that they had a Power to judge whether he had discharged his trust or no.</p>
               <p>And lastly, that they might dispose of the <hi>King</hi> as they would; having gone thus far, as it were a He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald of defyance to pronounce open Hostility, they sent the King nineteen Propositions, with a choice of War or Peace upon refusal or condescention, the Chief of which were,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Lords</hi> and others of the <hi>Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel,</hi> and all great Officers of State, both at home and abroad, be put from their Employments, and from his Council, save only such as should be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by both Houses of Parliament, and none put into their places but by approbation of the said <hi>House,</hi> and that the Privy Councellors should take two Oaths for the Execution of their places, as should be agreed on by both <hi>Houses.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the great Affairs of the Kingdom should be resolved and transacted only in Parliament, and such as should presume to do any thing contrary to be reserved to the Censure of the Parliament.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Lord High Steward, High Constable, Lord Chancellour, Lord Treasurer, Privy Seal, Earl Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shal, Lord Admiral, Warden</hi> of the <hi>Cinque Ports, Deputy</hi> of <hi>Ireland, Chancellor</hi> of the <hi>Chequer; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:43770:48"/> of <hi>State,</hi> two <hi>Chief Justices</hi> and <hi>Chief Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> should be chosen by the approbation of both <hi>Houses,</hi> that the Votes of Popish <hi>Lords</hi> in the <hi>House,</hi> should be taken away, that the Church should be reformed as both <hi>Houses</hi> should advise, that the <hi>Militia</hi> should be setled in the Parliament.</p>
               <p>That the Peers by Bill should be restrained from Acting and Voting in the <hi>House,</hi> unless admitted with the consent of both <hi>Houses.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the King should raise no Guards but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, in case of actual <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the sending of these Propositions, which was no more then <hi>Actual Rebellion</hi> in it self, and that his Majestie had refused to grant them, they began on both sides to prepare for War.</p>
               <p>The King raised a Guard for his Person in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> and the Parliament thereupon having Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the King intended thereupon to make War upon the Parliament, gave order for Muster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Forces, and raising Money, of which they made the Earl of <hi>Essex</hi> General.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Rebellion</hi> thus begun, many Battles and Skirmishes were fought with various success, tho for a while with much more advantage to the <hi>King</hi> than the <hi>Parliament,</hi> who finding that the King made good his ground so well in the <hi>South,</hi> and that his <hi>Lieutenant</hi> prospered so victoriously in the <hi>North,</hi> were forced to call in the <hi>Scots</hi> for their assistants, for whose satisfaction they Sacrificed <hi>Arch-bishop Laud,</hi> and entered into that solemn <hi>Leag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> wherewith they cemented their Iniquity together, and like <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates,</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:43770:49"/> or like so many <hi>Catilines</hi> and <hi>Cetheguses,</hi> they in dangerous attempts, vow'd to live in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Enterprizes.</p>
               <p>In two Battles the Parliament were eminently victorious in that of <hi>Marston Moor,</hi> and that other called the second <hi>Nembury</hi> Fight; by which the Parliament believing that <hi>Essex</hi> did not Prosecute as he ought to have done, the advantages he had got, the Parliament began to have an ill opinion of him, and from hence the new modelling of the <hi>Army</hi> was projected; to which purpose, as every Change begins with Outcries, the noise of Justice was now against Delinquents. And here we must begin to observe the first Fruits of Gods revenge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Maintainers and Abettors of this <hi>Rebellion,</hi> which <hi>Heaven</hi> did afterwards so fully Prosecute to the ignominious fall and destruction of so many detestible <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Regicides.</hi> For who were these Delinquents, but such as have been their Creatures, and done them that Service which enabled them to play the pranks they p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The first was Sir <hi>Alexander Carew,</hi> and the two <hi>Hothams</hi> both Father and Son, who for their Disloyalty to their <hi>Soveraign,</hi> were put to death for being false to <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traitors.</hi> This was the same Person, who being desired by <hi>Sir Bevil Greenvile,</hi> not to give his Vote against the Bill of <hi>Attainder</hi> of the <hi>Lord Strafford,</hi> made answer, that if he were sure he should be the next Man that should suffer upon the same <hi>Scaffold,</hi> with the same <hi>Ax,</hi> he would give his consent to the passing it.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:43770:49"/>
               <p>Some few days after, both the <hi>Hothams</hi> were Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed at the same place, for endeavouring to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray <hi>Hull</hi> to the King, and holding Correspondence with the Marquiss of <hi>New-Castle,</hi> of whom it will be enough to observe what his late Majesty himself observed upon their last ends.</p>
               <p>Nor did a single Vengeance serve the turn; the cutting of one Head in a Family is not enough to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piate for the affront done to the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weal.</hi> The Eldest Son must be involved in the Punishment, as he was infected with the Sin of his Father, against the Father of his Country, Root and Branch God cut off in one day.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>That which makes me more pity him vvas, that after he began to have some Inclinations of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for his Sin, and reparation of his Duty to me, he should be so <hi>unhappy</hi> as to fall into the <hi>Hands</hi> of <hi>their Justice</hi> and not <hi>my Mercy,</hi> vvho could as vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly have forgiven <hi>H m</hi> as <hi>He</hi> could have asked that favour of <hi>Me.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Poor Gentleman, he is now become a notable Monument of unprosperous Loyalty; teaching the world by so sad an unfortunate Spectacle, that the rude carriage of a Subject carries always its own Vengeance as an unseparable shadow with it, and those oft prove the most Fatal and Impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Executioners of it, who were the first Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployers in the <hi>Service.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But now the Presbyterian <hi>Democraticks</hi> went vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorously on with their new Model, which <hi>Essex, Manch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ster</hi> and <hi>Denbigh</hi> perceiving, that they might not be seen to have their Commissions taken
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:43770:50"/> from them, resigned them of their own accord. And this was the reward which <hi>Essex</hi> received for all the good <hi>Services</hi> which he performed for a Nest of Rebels against their Prince; who having now lost the opportunity of blessing the Kingdom with a Peace, when it lay in his Power; and to which he was Courted but a while before by the King at <hi>Lestithiel,</hi> withdrew himself in discontent to his House at <hi>Eltham</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> where not long after he died, not without suspicion of being poysoned by them, for whom he had so far blasted his Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in heading their unnatural Rebellion. They who were before such great adorers of his Person, now scorned and contemned him like Adulterous kindness, which changed into Hatred and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, the admiration of those whom his Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity had estranged from their first love to their Prince, who ceased not to prosecute his Honour with publick Dicteries and ridiculous Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>Print.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By <hi>his Death</hi> it plainly appeared that the <hi>Soul</hi> of <hi>Presbytery</hi> was departed, which had actuated that self-designing, formless <hi>Schism</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> to a mad and infatuated Division in the <hi>State,</hi> and armed its <hi>Hands</hi> with Force and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to propagate its Dominion and Magisterial Usurpation. For when this first great <hi>Pillar</hi> of it fell, it submitted to its fatal <hi>Period.</hi> The great Blaze and Flames it had raised, waning into a glimmering and suspicious Light, were lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on even as Meteors or Exhallations rather than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fixed or certain Luminary.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:43770:50"/>
               <p>For by this time the <hi>Army</hi> was new modell'd, and committed to the Conduct of Sir <hi>Thomas Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi> as General, and <hi>Cromwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> as Lieutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, all <hi>Ess<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x</hi>'s Officers being Discarded with a flea in the Ears, instead of the promised payment of their <hi>Arrears,</hi> (a just reward for their Fidelity to Disloyalty;) so that <hi>Cromwell,</hi> who far exceeded the General in <hi>Policy</hi> and <hi>Design,</hi> though not in <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,</hi> had the opportunity to Garble the Officers of the new moulded <hi>Army</hi> as he pleas'd himself; however he must do his work before he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Quarrel with his Masters. Thereupon the General and he fell to their business, and that with such an unfortunate Gale of Prosperity, That the King was not only beaten out of the Field, and strip'd of all his Garrisons, but was forc'd to flye to the <hi>Perfidious Scots</hi> for Refuge: out of whose hands when the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> had bought him, then <hi>Cromwell</hi> high in Repute for the Fame of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Conduct, and in great esteem with the <hi>Army,</hi> began to play his own Cards, making use of his own <hi>Independants</hi> and their <hi>Adherents, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists, Anabaptists, Fifth-Monarchy Men,</hi> and <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> all included under the Name of <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> of which there were a great number in the <hi>Army</hi> and several by this time crept into the House, enough to put in doubts, and delay the Proceedings of the contrary party: and sometimes upon an opportunity of a thin House, to carry a Vote in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of <hi>Cromwell.</hi> Neither was <hi>Cromwell</hi> so bad a Scholar, but that he knew how to practise the same <hi>Falsities, Dissimulations, Perjuries,</hi> and <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:43770:51"/> against his <hi>Pr sbyterian Masters,</hi> which they had practised against their Sovereign Lord.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> began with <hi>Tumults</hi> and <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny,</hi> so did He; to which purpose, he and his Son <hi>Ireton</hi> contriv'd a way to make the <hi>Army</hi> Rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Parliam nt,</hi> that had payed them all along, and under whose Banner they had hitherto fought, by spreading a Rumour, That the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt,</hi> now they had the King, intended to disband them, and cheat them of their <hi>Arrears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Army</hi> enraged at this, erect a Council a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themselves of two Souldiers out of every <hi>Troop</hi> and <hi>Company,</hi> to Consult for the good of the <hi>Army,</hi> and for the peace and safety of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> so that whatever <hi>Cromwell</hi> would have done he needed nothing to make them do it; and the effect of their first Consultation was, to take the King from <hi>Holmby</hi> out of the Hands of the <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and carry him into the <hi>Army,</hi> whereby <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> thought he had gotten such an advantage, that he said openly, <hi>That now he had the Parliament in his Pocket, and the City too.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place, as the Parliament by Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Attainders had depriv'd the King of the choicest of his Confidents and Couns<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llors, so <hi>Cromwell</hi> sends to have the House purg'd, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Suspension of eleven Members at once, whom he knew to be his most potent and most able <hi>Adversaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which when the <hi>Parliament</hi> refused to do, and had drawn the City to raise Forces, and Man their Lines in their Defence, the City it self, after a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:43770:51"/> Bustle to no purpose, was in some measure brought to confess their deserved punishment of their former Disloyalty, by feeling the Effects of that <hi>Tyranny</hi> which they had brought upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and constrain'd to relinquish their <hi>Militia,</hi> to desert the eleven Members, to deliver up their Line of <hi>Communication</hi> and the <hi>Tower,</hi> to disband their Forces, and turn out all <hi>Essex</hi>'s Old Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and to draw off their Guards from the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and to suffer the <hi>Army</hi> to March in Triumph through their Principal Streets.</p>
               <p>During these Stirs, several of the Armies driven Members of both Houses with both their Speakers fled to the Army, and Voted in a <hi>Parliam ntary</hi> way in the <hi>Council of War,</hi> while they that remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed behind chose themselves new Speakers, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admitted the seven of their number: but the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my having ended their <hi>Triumphant March,</hi> released their Fugitive Members, and restored the <hi>Speak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs</hi> to their <hi>Chairs,</hi> so that the eleven finding the place too hot, were forced to quit that <hi>Hive,</hi> where they had so long reign'd <hi>Master Bees,</hi> for all together.</p>
               <p>And now the <hi>Presbyterian Party</hi> too late percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the fatal Errors into which they had run themselves, and the <hi>Ruin</hi> that was falling upon their Heads, whither out of a true Repentance, or to obviate the Progress of their Enemies, began to think of reconciling themselves to their injur'd and slighted Prince. But whither it were, that <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> well knew that their Repentance was but forc'd, and out of necessity, and therefore reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them for the ensuing <hi>Ignominies</hi> that befel
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:43770:52"/> them for the Crimes of their former Disobedience, all their Consultations and Contrivances against the <hi>Army</hi> were now as unsuccessful, as they were prosperous against their Sovereign.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Fugitive Members</hi> being replac'd, they who had sat in the absence of the two <hi>Speakers,</hi> sat in such a servile fear, that they durst not dissent from what the contrary Faction propounded. The effects of which was, That the <hi>Independants</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately displac'd all Governours, and put in Men of their own Party that they could confide in; the <hi>Militias</hi> of <hi>London, Westminster,</hi> and <hi>Southwark,</hi> were divided, and the Works and Lines of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication</hi> dismantl'd.</p>
               <p>Having thus levell'd all things before them, they procur'd an Abolition of all Orders, Votes, and Ordinances, that had pass'd in the absence of the two <hi>Speakers.</hi> And yet this Ordinance of Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilation would not pass among the more stubborn of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> till the <hi>Speaker</hi> pull'd out a Letter from <hi>Cromwell,</hi> taxing them with what was truly cast in their <hi>Teeth</hi> in reference to their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, though not so deservedly for what they then had done, with <hi>Treason, Treachery,</hi> and <hi>Breach of Trust,</hi> declaring further, That if they should presume to come there before they had clear'd themselves from assenting to such and such Votes, they should sit at their peril, and that he would take them as Prisoners of War, and try them by a Council of War. And to make his words good, an Impeachment was carryed up to the <hi>House of Lords,</hi> upon which the Earls of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:43770:52"/> Lincoln,</hi> and <hi>Middlesex,</hi> the Lords <hi>Berkley, Willoughby</hi> of <hi>Parkham, Hunsdon,</hi> and <hi>Maynard,</hi> were Committed to the <hi>Black Rod:</hi> several of the <hi>House of Commons</hi> were likewise suspended, and others committed to the <hi>Tower,</hi> together with the <hi>Lord Major,</hi> and several of the <hi>Aldermen,</hi> while <hi>Points</hi> and <hi>Massey</hi> were forc'd to flye into <hi>Holland.</hi> And thus by a just <hi>Retaliation</hi> of <hi>Providence,</hi> they who had made their Prince a Captive were now become most miserable slaves to their own <hi>Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the subsequent Prevarications and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Overtures made by <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to the King, and their close restraint of him to supple him to Condescention, we pass them over, as hastening to the <hi>Catastrophe</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who were the first Authors of the <hi>Rebellion.</hi> This is only to be said, <hi>That those Shufflings and Cuttings with His Majesty had so enraged the Discontents of the People, that the Nation was in several parts almost in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd in a second War: what with the</hi> Kentish In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection, <hi>the</hi> Revolt <hi>in Wales, and the</hi> Scotish In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion; <hi>so that the Parliament seeing so many Dangers appear at one and the same time with doubtful Faces, and fearing the Dubiousness of success, began to think of making some Provision for their own safety, dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more especially the</hi> Scotch Storm; <hi>to which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, they recall'd,</hi> Their Votes of Non Addresses, <hi>and voted the Kings Condescentions a sufficient Ground to proceed to a personal Treaty, with Honour, Freedom, and Safety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Fairfax</hi> having Dissipated the Southern
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:43770:53"/> Storms, and <hi>Cromwell</hi> having clear'd <hi>Wales,</hi> and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly defeated the <hi>Scots,</hi> and both returning home Arm'd with fresh Lawrels, and now more Insolent with success, call'd their presumptious slaves to a severe account, which now must pay off all their old Scores with <hi>Ignominy</hi> and <hi>Dismission.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For now these <hi>Catiffs</hi> understanding the Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the House, resolv'd to play no longer with the weak Read of <hi>Priviledge,</hi> but with a bold Sword dissolve the <hi>Oracle</hi> of their Villanies; To this purpose, <hi>Pride, Huson,</hi> and some other Officers, having had some Conferences together in <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster Hall</hi> with the <hi>Speaker,</hi> the Dore being shut, sent in a Paper to the <hi>House of Commons,</hi> requiring the Impeach'd Members, and Major General <hi>Brown,</hi> as Guilty of calling in <hi>Hamilton,</hi> to be secur'd and brought to Justice, and that the 90 odd Members, who refus'd to Vote against the late <hi>Scotch Engagement,</hi> might be immediately suspend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the House, and that all such faithful <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mbers,</hi> who were Innocent of those Votes, would by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation acquit themselves of those Votes.</p>
               <p>To this Paper they admitted no demur, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently brought three or four Regiments of Horse and Foot, and set strong Guards at the House Doors, the Lobby <hi>Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs,</hi> and every where about the Palace, admitting none but <hi>Parliament Men</hi> into the Hall, where the two forementioned Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels and <hi>Sir Hardress W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ller</hi> violently seized se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the <hi>Memb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs</hi> whom <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> fitting, and forcibly carryed them away <hi>P soners.</hi> Of these a Catalogue was afterwards taken by <hi>Hugh
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:43770:53"/> Peters,</hi> after which they were <hi>thrust</hi> into Hell, where they were kept without any Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all Night, and the next day committed under Guard to several Inns in the <hi>Strand;</hi> about <hi>one Hundred</hi> and <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xty</hi> more were by the same Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders debarred entrance into the House, besides <hi>Forty</hi> more that voluntarily withdrew themselves, most of the <hi>Forty M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mbers,</hi> after many Expostu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and their Protestations in vain against the force put upon them, were at length released. <hi>Ireton</hi> insolently biding them look to themselves, and how they acted any thing against the present Government and Army at their Peril.</p>
               <p>And thus were the mighty Grandees of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery cast down from their Seats, where they had so long usurped their Soveraign's Dominion, and laid the Foundation of his utter Ruin. Nor did this <hi>Jeroboam</hi> of a <hi>Cromwel,</hi> rending the Tyranny out of their <hi>Rebellious Hands,</hi> leave them so much as one Tribe to Domineer over: But first pull'd 'em out as it were by the Ears, then Imprisoned 'em, and afterwards with shame and Ignominy dismissed 'em, Cashier'd, Discarded, Contemned and Scorn'd by those whom they themselves had mounted into the Saddle of their own Illegal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, And this was the Just reward of the first F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llies and Treasons of the Independants.</p>
               <p>And now was the whole Body of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment reduced to an Inconsiderable <hi>Juncto,</hi> wholly at the Devotion of their Great <hi>Sultan Cromwel,</hi> who nevertheless served them outwardly with great Diligence, till by their assistance he had most
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:43770:54"/>
                  <hi>Inhumanly</hi> &amp; <hi>Irreligiously</hi> taken away the <hi>Kings Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that being done, and himself now swelled to that excessive bulk of loftiness, not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined within the narrow limits of a General-ship, as he that had so lately reduced <hi>Ireland,</hi> conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Scotland,</hi> overthrown the King at <hi>Worcester,</hi> thought it now time to reap the benefit of his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessful Labours. And therefore looking upon the <hi>Juncto</hi> of his pretended Masters, only as an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and feeble Crew, that stood upon his Crut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, yet threatned to beat him with them, and to <hi>Essex</hi> him out of all his Grandeur, he resolved to cut the Gordian knot of all their Intreagues.</p>
               <p>To this purpose attended with <hi>Lambert, Harison</hi> and some other of his great Officers, he entered the House, and after a short speech, wherein he shewed the Reasons and necessities of their Disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, he declared the <hi>Juncto</hi> to be dissolved, and desired the Members to depart.</p>
               <p>Upon which <hi>Harison</hi> peremptorily bid the <hi>Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> leave the Chair, which he refusing to do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out order of the House; or till he was pulled out, <hi>Harrison</hi> desired him to lend him his Hand, and gently heav'd him out. <hi>Cromwel</hi> also commanded their Bauble as he called it the Mace, to be taken away, and so having turned the Wretches out of Doors, lock't 'em up, and clapt Guards upon 'em, and about all the Avenues into the Palace, to prevent those Spirits from possessing it again.</p>
               <p>The News of the fall of these <hi>Lucifers</hi> was quickly spread through the City, and from thence over the Country, where it was related and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:43770:54"/> with all imaginable gladness, while the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers slunk away muttering to themselves the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front they had received, and laying their Heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether how to retrieve themselves; for loath they were to acknowledg their <hi>Dissolution,</hi> but whatever they fancied to the contrary, raving at this Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Audaciousness of their Servant as they called him, <hi>Cromwel</hi> their Master, minded it not, but went on with his Business.</p>
               <p>Certainly Fate never plaid such a frolick part, nor was there ever such a Scene of Mirth in all her Mazes and Varieties of Government, so unusual it is for the greatest and most potent of wicked men, to survive the Infamy and Dishonour of their Actions, unless it be to live the Ignominy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of themselves. But as if God would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the threatned punishment of the fifth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, these unparallel'd Parricides were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to out live the Desire of Life, and to see all their Greatness buried, their Reputation abroad, and their Dread at Home fallen into such Ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Disgrace, that it was the common Theme of Ballads, the most scurrilous and contemptible that was to be imagined. On the other side <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> was more applauded by the People for this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then any of his Victories in the War, while none were more derided and scorned than those Reformado's of Petty Princes.</p>
               <p>Thus the two first <hi>Scenes</hi> of this <hi>Tragical Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> being past; the next was the <hi>Scene</hi> of <hi>Protector<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi> which concluding with the <hi>Tyrants Life;</hi> the <hi>fifth</hi> were but the struglings and uttermost efforts
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:43770:55"/> of Anarchy and Confusion, drawing to a Mortal Dissolution, which ended at length in the happy and long panted-after Restauration of his present <hi>Majesty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then it was, that Divine Vengeance having trac'd the <hi>Murderers</hi> of their <hi>Martyr'd Soveraign,</hi> at last through several <hi>Mazes</hi> overtook them, the Iron Hand of Justice delivering them up to the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment due to their unparallel'd Impiety. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though it were thought fit, as well to shew his <hi>Majesties</hi> Clemency to the lesser guilty of his undutiful People, that an Act of Oblivion should pass for the general safety of the Nation, yet that his Justice might appear as equally Resplendent in not suffering such an <hi>unexampl'd Parricide</hi> to go vvith <hi>unexampled Impunity,</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> thought it altogether as necessary to Exclude from <hi>Mercy,</hi> the <hi>Chief Authors</hi> and <hi>Actors</hi> in the <hi>Late Rebellion</hi> and more <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rrid Perpetration,</hi> such vvhom <hi>Death</hi> had spared, as <hi>Sacrifices</hi> to the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Honour</hi> of their <hi>Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thereupon a Commission of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer</hi> was issu'd out for the Tryal of the several Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders according to their merits; for no less then two days of Judgment will suffice for <hi>Treason</hi> and <hi>Disloyalty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of these there were two sorts, some who were reserv'd to such Forfeitures, as should by Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be declared; of which the principal were, Sir <hi>Arthur Hasterigg, Oliver</hi> St. <hi>John William, Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thall</hi> the Speaker, <hi>Nye</hi> the Minister, <hi>Burlin</hi> of <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> and some Sequestrators and Officers of the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:43770:55"/> Army; as <hi>Desborough, Pine, Butler, Ireton,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The other <hi>Classis</hi> was, of those who were <hi>Tryed</hi> at the <hi>Old-Bayly,</hi> and the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> by Vertue of the Commission aforesaid, directed to the Lord Mayor and Judges, of which the Lord <hi>Bridgeman,</hi> then Lord Chief Baron was the Chief. And of these some were immediately Condemned and Executed, others Condemned and Remanded to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Prisons, where they lay under Sentence, to be Executed at the Kings Pleasure.</p>
               <p>The Persons Condemned and Executed were, Captain <hi>Thomas Harrison,</hi> Apprehended in <hi>Stafford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire: John Carew,</hi> Brother to Sir <hi>Alexander Carew,</hi> Beheaded by the Long-Parliament, in 1644.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>All Executed at <hi>Charing-Cross,</hi> and <hi>Tyburn.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Cook,</hi> the Solicitor.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> taken in <hi>Southwark.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Scot.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gregory Clements.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Adrian Scroope.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Jones.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Francis Hacker.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Daniel Axtel.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Colonel Okey.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Miles Corbet.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Bearkstead.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Sir <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nry Vane</hi> Tryed the Year following in <hi>Trinity Term,</hi> and Executed on <hi>Tower-Hill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Persons that received Sentence, but were remanded to Prison under Sentence of Death, to be Executed at the King's pleasure were,
<list>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:43770:56"/>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Hardress Waller.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Heveningham.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Colonel <hi>Henry Martin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Owen Row,</hi> a Silk-man of <hi>London.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Austin Garland,</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Man for <hi>Quinbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry Smith,</hi> a Lawyer in <hi>Leicester-shire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Tichburn.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Colonel <hi>George Fleetwood.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Temple</hi> of <hi>Sussex.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Waite</hi> of <hi>Rutland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter Temple,</hi> a Linnen-Draper's Apprentice in <hi>Friday-Street.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Lilburn, John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi>'s Brother.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gilbert Millington.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vincent Potter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Downes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simon Meyne.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Major General <hi>Lambert</hi> received the Sentence of Death with Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> but regard being had of his submissive deportment at his Tryal, he was reprieved after Sentence at the Bar, and remanded to Prison.</p>
               <p>The Lord <hi>Mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>son,</hi> Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nry Mildmay,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wallop,</hi> were sent for to the Bar of the Houses then sitting, where their Estates were declared Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scate, they themselves degraded from all <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Armes</hi> of Gentillity; and farther Sentenced, <hi>To be Drawn from the</hi> Tower <hi>through the City to</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn <hi>upon Hurdles every</hi> 30th. <hi>of</hi> January, <hi>and so back with Halters about their Necks, and to suffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Imprisonment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Carcasses also of <hi>Cromwell, Ireton,</hi> and <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaw,</hi> were digged out of the Ground from those sumptuous Monuments, which as they Thron'd it in their Life-time, they had usurp'd at their Dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hs.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:43770:56"/> They were drawn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Cart from <hi>Westminster</hi> to the <hi>Red-Lyon</hi> in <hi>Holbourn,</hi> and thence on <hi>Sledges</hi> to <hi>Tyburn,</hi> where the Corps were taken out of the Coffins, and Hang'd at three Corners of the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows from ten a Clock till Sun-seting, and then the Heads being cut off to be plac'd upon <hi>Westminster-Hall,</hi> their Bodies were Buried in a deep Hole un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Gallows.</p>
               <p>This end at length had a long Rebellion, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by all the Force, the Youth, the Wealth, and most crafty Head-pieces of a whole Nation, at last shatter'd to pieces, and delivered up to condign Punishment, and the effects of divine Vengeance, after a long and haughty Tyranny, by their own Ambition, and Divisions among themselves: lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this Indeleble Truth of the Proverb behind them, <hi>That Honest Men came by their own, through the falling out of Thieves and Traytors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Rebellious Scots,</hi> who lent their help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand to their <hi>Covenanting Brethren</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and at last sold their Sovereign to the Scaffold, they liv'd to see their Country quite subdu'd by <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> who after the fatal overthrow of <hi>Dunbar,</hi> over-ran the whole Kingdom, impos'd his own Judges upon them, and kept them enslav'd by the Curb of four such <hi>Cittadels</hi> as the Liberty of that Nation was never subjected to before.</p>
               <p>No less bitter was the Cup of which the <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Irish</hi> tasted at the long run. For being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster'd by <hi>Cromwell,</hi> they were reduc'd to that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they were forc'd to surrender their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states and Habitations to the <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> of the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:43770:57"/>
                  <hi>English,</hi> who forbore not to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, <hi>That they pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed their Estates but during their pleasure, and till they could get Planters to put into their Rooms;</hi> So that when they could hold out no longer, the best Articles they could get was, to abandon their <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Soil,</hi> and to transport themselves into <hi>Forreign Service.</hi> Providence so ordering, That they should be forced to seek their Bread in forreign Exile, who had disturbed the Peace of their own Country.</p>
               <p>And these have been the fatal Fruits of <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> against the lawful Sovereigns of <hi>England</hi> from before the Conquest, to the Restauration of His present Majesty; which they who will not apply to themselves, have nothing to do, but to adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the same Vengeance from <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the same Punishments and Rewards of Treason and Disloyalty from <hi>Men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:43770:57"/>
            <head>Some Books Printed for, and Sold by, <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Annals of King <hi>James,</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the First, Containing a faithful and impartial Account of the Great Affairs of State and Transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Parliaments in <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Folio.</hi> Wherein several material Passages Relating to the late Civil Wars (not m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntioned in former Histories) are made known in particular, some of Mr. <hi>Rushworth</hi>'s Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stakes and Omissions. As first the Case of the Devorce of the Earl of <hi>Essex</hi> from his Countess, which had so great Influence on the ensuing Troubles, Related from the Original Proceedings in that Court.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> The True Cause of the Troubles in our Church, <hi>viz.</hi> The Connivance of some Church-men at the Diss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs from the Government of the Church, as Established by Law, and the Favour found at Court from great Persons there.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> King <hi>James</hi> not so much Influenced by <hi>Gonda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> as is Related by Mr. <hi>Rushworth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> The Three Estates in Parliament who they were, in King <hi>James</hi>'s Speech in Parliament; <hi>1620.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> An Authentick and Impartial Account of the beginning of the Troubles in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Wars which ensued.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> The True State of our late Civil Wars, their Beginnings, Causes, who the Aggressors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The rest are too large to take notice here, but may be seen in the Preface.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43770:58"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Varenius's Geography</hi> in <hi>Folio English,</hi> Illustra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with many Copper Cuts.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Willis's</hi> Works in <hi>Folio, English.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The History of the <hi>Irish Rebellion,</hi> traced from many preceeding Acts to the grand Eruption, the 23d. of <hi>October, 1641.</hi> and thence pursued to the <hi>Act of Settlement, 1662.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tracts Written by <hi>John Selden</hi> of the <hi>Inner-Temple,</hi> Esq and Translated by the Eminent Dr. <hi>A. L.</hi> The 1st, <hi>Jani Anglorum facies altera,</hi> with large Notes thereupon. 2ly, <hi>Englands Epinomis.</hi> 3ly, Of the Original of Ecclesiastical Jurisdictions of Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The 4th, of the Disposition or Administration of intestate Goods.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Scrivener</hi>'s Body of Divinity.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Cumber</hi> on the <hi>Liturgy</hi> in <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Sam</hi>'s <hi>Britannia.</hi> Ogleby<hi>'s</hi> History of <hi>Affrica, Asia,</hi> and <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bishop of St. <hi>Davids</hi>'s Vindication of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops Rights to Vote in Capital Cases—his seasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Corrective.</p>
            <p>The Compleat Catalogue to the end of <hi>Easter Term, 1684.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Bishop of <hi>Lincoln</hi>'s Observations, and Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions on <hi>Pope Pius</hi> the 5th. his <hi>Bull</hi> against <hi>Queen Elizabeth:</hi> wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unto is annexed the <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Pope Paul</hi> the 3d. against King <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Cumber</hi>'s Vindication of the Divine Right of Tythes.</p>
            <p>Bishop of <hi>Cork</hi>'s Perswasive to all Protestants.</p>
            <p>Religion and Loyalty supporting each other, in Vindication of the Loyal Addressors.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43770:58"/>
            <p>Bishop of St. <hi>Davids</hi>'s <hi>Billa Vera,</hi> or Argument of <hi>Ignoramus —</hi> his short way to a lasting Settlem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, and Answer to <hi>Sidney's</hi> Speech—his Advice to a sound Protestant and Proselyte of <hi>Rome</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll'd back.</p>
            <p>Three Sermons of Dr. <hi>Standishes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two of Mr. <hi>Richard Werge</hi> of <hi>New-Castle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmon of Dr. <hi>Manue</hi> before the King.</p>
            <p>Two of Dr. <hi>Dixons</hi>'s Prebend, of <hi>Rochester.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Ward</hi>'s Sermon of <hi>Blandford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ogleby</hi>'s <hi>Essop</hi> in <hi>English,</hi> adorn'd with <hi>160</hi> Sculp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>A Discourse of Natural and Moral Impotency.</p>
            <p>Bishop of St. <hi>Davids</hi>'s Answer to <hi>Melius Inquiren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi>—his Answer to the <hi>Protestant Reconciler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brown</hi>'s Treatise of Preternatural Tumours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mecket</hi>'s <hi>Tractatus de politia Eccles. Anglicanae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reduction of <hi>Ireland</hi> to the Crown of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Smith</hi>'s Rhetorick, the Fifth Edition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Humphrey</hi>'s Resolution of Conscience.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Byan</hi>'s Eight Sermons, Preached before His Majesty in his Exile.</p>
            <p>Friendly Conference between a Minister and a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, two parts.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Duport</hi>'s Poems. <hi>Seneca</hi> with <hi>Farnaby. Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card</hi>'s Hebrew Grammer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Essop</hi>'s Fables, Greek and Latin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compend. Politicum:</hi> An Account of the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 3d.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martindale</hi>'s Book of Surveying.</p>
            <p>Book of Riddles.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:43770:59"/>
               <p>THere is also Published a Book Entituled, <hi>The Royal Apology,</hi> or an Answer to the <hi>Reb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls Plea:</hi> Wherein the most Noted <hi>Anti-Monarchical Tenents, First,</hi> Published by <hi>Doleman</hi> the <hi>Jesuite,</hi> to promote a <hi>Bill</hi> of <hi>Exclusion</hi> against King <hi>JAMES, Secondly,</hi> Practised by <hi>Bradshaw</hi> and the <hi>Regicides</hi> in the actual Murder of King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the First. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Republished by <hi>Sidney</hi> and the <hi>Associators,</hi> to <hi>Depose</hi> and <hi>Murder</hi> His <hi>Present MAJESTY,</hi> are distinctly considered. With a <hi>Parallel</hi> between <hi>Doleman, Bradshaw, Sidney,</hi> and other of the True Protestant <hi>Party. London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> and are to be sold by <hi>Randolph Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1684. <hi>Price</hi> 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Judgment of an <hi>Anonymous Writer,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing these following Particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> A Law for Disabling a <hi>Papist</hi> to <hi>Inherit</hi> the <hi>Crown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Execution of <hi>Penal Laws</hi> against <hi>Protestant Dissenters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> A Bill of <hi>Comprehension.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All briefly Discussed in a Letter from beyond the Seas to a <hi>Dissenter,</hi> ten Years ago; The Second Addition. London, <hi>Printed by</hi> T. B. <hi>for</hi> Robert Clavel, <hi>and are to be sold by</hi> Randolph Taylor, <hi>near</hi> Stationers Hall. 1684.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43770:59"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>